<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Il putanismo di Roma, or, The history of the whores and whoredom of the popes, cardinals, and clergy of Rome discovered by a conclave of ladies convened for the election of a new pope / written in Italian by the author of Cardinalismo and Nepotismo ; and now made English by I.D., Esq.</title>
            <title>Putanismo di Roma. English</title>
            <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1340A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36249</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15620570</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15620570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1151:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Il putanismo di Roma, or, The history of the whores and whoredom of the popes, cardinals, and clergy of Rome discovered by a conclave of ladies convened for the election of a new pope / written in Italian by the author of Cardinalismo and Nepotismo ; and now made English by I.D., Esq.</title>
                  <title>Putanismo di Roma. English</title>
                  <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 136 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>To the reader signed: A.D.A.S.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Leti.</note>
                  <note>Running title: The whoredome of Rome.</note>
                  <note>Contains numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, torn, and tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Papal courts.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:104221:1"/>
            <p> 
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104221:1"/>
            <p>Il Putaniſmo Di <hi>Roma,</hi> Or the Hiſtory of the WHORES
And Whoredom of the Popes, Cardinals And Clergy of ROME. Diſcovered by a
Conclave of Ladies convened for the Election of a new Pope.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Italian</hi> by the Author of
<hi>Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſmo</hi> and <hi>Nepotiſmo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now made Engliſh by <hi>I. D.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104221:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104221:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Author</hi> to thoſe that are curious.</head>
            <p>WRiting in this age is nothing elſe but an itching of the hand,
whilſt they write with ſo much liberty, that we must abſolutely believe
the Intellect hath no ſhare in the manual operation. Beſides tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd,
though that the hand oppoſeth the pen with ſo great ſilence and
ſecrecy, that the judgment is alſo excluded from reading; for many things
would be omitted in writing, if the judgment and not the hand did manage the
affair. If writing were an incurable French diſeaſe, the world in a ſhort
time would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of Writers, if I deceive not my ſelf; but I fear I am
deceiv'd, for to be real, the Art of Writing at preſent is a deviliſh
diſtemper, and yet not feared; how then can a venereal diſtemper be
dreaded, if the Devil himſelf cannot terrifie Writers?</p>
            <p>As for my own particular, I never had an inclination to write for
others, judging it better to let others write for me, but ſeeing ſo great a
Vorago of Manuſcripts ſcattered abroad in every corner of <hi>Rome,</hi> it
did ſo rouſe my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,<pb facs="tcp:104221:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat I
could do no leſs, but enter the Liſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the reſt; yet before I took
my pen in hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ery ſeriouſly
conſider'd of the ſubjest; and thought with my ſelf, that in a time when
the Chair was vacant, it behooved me to write with liberty concerning the
publick ſcandal of thoſe vices which at other times walk mask't in
<hi>Rome.</hi> I had a deſire by all means to be in the Conclave, that in a
place of ſuch clamour, I might find out a worthy ſubject to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talize my
name at my firſt appearing in Print: And whilſt I communicated this my
thought to a friend of mine, whom I did very much eſteem; his She-confident,
who was then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, did adviſe, or to ſpeak more properly command me
(becauſe that Curtezans bear the ſway at <hi>Rome</hi>) to undertake a
deſcription of the General Conclave, which the Court-Ladies of pleaſure had
taken up a reſolution to create in order to the finding out of a ſubject
concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Election of a Pope that might be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuited to their
interest. I did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliſh the ſentiment of this good Lady, who
though ſhe ſaid it only in raillery, did never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs in good earnest
leave a great impresſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon my ſpirit; Inſomuch as that very evening I
undertook the work, and in a ſhort time finiſhed it ſo, as it is now
preſented to you. Read it then, not as mine, but the work of<pb facs="tcp:104221:3"/>thoſe excellent, or if you pleaſe curious Wits, that depriv'd me of
it, before I had time to peruſe it; telling me that I muſt publiſh it to
enrich the more abſtruſe ſtudies of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that are
ſcrupulous. In truth my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to print it, but in time, knowing very
well, that in Rancounters of this nature, it is convenient to proceed with
deliberation; but my good Friends made me this reply, that it was not now the
cuſtom to be ſlow in printing, ſince all perſons are as nimble at the
Preſs, as thoſe that ſlide upon the Ice. In fine, all that I could obtain
was one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to write thee Reader, theſe two lines by way of Apology, and
to give thee to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I ſtudy thy ſatisfaction.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. D. A. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104221:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104221:4"/>
            <head>Il Puttaniſmo di <hi>Roma,</hi> OR The Whoredome of
<hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe diſtreſſed and miſerable City of <hi>Rome</hi> did not
only live under a grievous and pitiful, but cruel and horrible ſervitude, as
was prepar'd for her to undergo for the future, and had ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd her
mind to the patient enduring of her diſgraces, that ſhe ſeem'd to be
cloath'd with conſtancy, and to emulate thoſe that are Hydropical: When as
fortune, who had obſtinately reſolv'd to perſecute her, envying her
undauntedneſs, as if it were the undoubted reproach of the decay of her
ſtrength, and the other virtues, did, by other inventions as ingenious as
tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, procure means to ſhake her out of that peaceable condition, by
the feigned apparition of a ſuddain blaze of probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that there was
ſome hope of her deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from ſuch perplexities and penal 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104221:5"/>torments, by bringing her to ſuſpect (as is now
notorious) the life of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Seventh to be of no continuance,
upon whoſe death the abſtract of her greateſt fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, and redreſs in
and by all things, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends: But ſince among the individual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who
chiefly conſtitute the ſaid City, the Ladies retain the moſt
conſiderable place, and conſpicuous number; whoſe ſeed is more fertile
then the graſs that grows in the field; theſe perſons ſeeing
themſelves generally ill-treated and deluded by this ſo ſtrange, unlawful
and horrid Popeſhip, from which they never can, could, or ever may expect
from the future, as long as ever it continues, any advantage or ſucceſs
imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but rather fear unexpected ruine and deſtruction: Becauſe the
Seneſes have by a certain quality of nature, or natural inſtinct ſo
abſolute and implacable an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy againſt the female ſex, that it
ſeems almoſt impoſſible there ſhould ever be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a
reconciliation or agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
            <p>It is reported by ſome Hiſtorians, that this took beginning
ever ſince ſome Eaſtern Merchants, <hi>anno</hi> 200 of the creation of
the world, did by the way of <hi>Ligorne</hi> import and tranſport ſome
contagious Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104221:5"/>that came from thoſe Provinces;
where the people have ſuch an averſion for the female ſex, that rather
then they will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their duty to them, will aſſume ſo much
boldneſs as to affront even the Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Gueſts of <hi>Lot</hi>
himſelf. Wherefore the modern infirmity of this new Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature is not
eaſily known at <hi>Rome,</hi> which the Patriarcheſs of the Brothel
houſe hath with ſo ſolicitous and exact diligence diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be
exerciſed various wayes, to be urged in divers buſineſſes, and ſo
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in ſeveral diſcourſes, to ſee if by any means poſſible
the Succeſſion of the new elected Pope may be made in ſome Creature of
theirs, or at leaſt in ſome Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject which they know by the natural
incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his genius, or experience of his proceedings, to adhere and be
devoted to their party, and in whom they might ſafely confide, without fear
of being betray'd.</p>
            <p>This advice ſucceeded the 20th of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, anno</hi> 1666.
at which time the ſeaſon of the year being then found ſufficiently
ſuited and proportion'd to whooriſh acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and chieflly by reaſon of
the great lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that is before that time in the months of <hi>June</hi>
and <hi>July,</hi> which precede it; in which they themſelves grant the
Students<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104221:6"/>in Phyſique a vacancy from labor, and only
reſerve themſelves to read them ſome ſmall Lecture by way of
diverſion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>contrarium Jeſuiticum in libro
Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum.</hi> Wherefore the major part of theſe Women, the better to
allure the Scholars, and thoſe that follow their natural Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, did
retire themſelves towards the near neighbouring Towns, and the moſt
pleaſant and ſuburbian places; for in things of this nature, being upheld
by the benefit of the winds, thoſe nauſeating matters which accompany their
conceits leſs agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or troubleſome to the genius of thoſe that
ſet them on, would ceaſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing that loſs of time in ſuch
a jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of affairs, is an abſolute prejudice to their intereſts, and
that their not being all unanimous in the agreement of their Votes, and
abetting an incluſive or excluſive ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt the Medicean
Florentine Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo great an enemy to them, and that of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ena,</hi>
of whom <hi>Chigi,</hi> was the head, their laſt Exterminator, were to bring
them a ſecond time under their former diſparagements.</p>
            <p>Whereupon at Madam <hi>Angela Salas,</hi> the moſt ſerene
Senioreſs of the Brothel-houſe, with her flying ſquadron <hi>Diana
Velletrana, Anna Felice a ſan Marco,</hi> and <hi>Bernardin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104221:6"/>alla Longara,</hi>
they came to this reſolution to advertiſe the venerable <hi>Cicia dello
Struz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo</hi> by an Expreſs, who was departed with <hi>Nina</hi> by the way
of <hi>Fraſcati,</hi> that ſhe ſhould immediatly come upon the place, and
be ready to negotiate, and agree to the incluſion of Cardinal <hi>Spada,</hi>
called <hi>Santa Suſanna,</hi> who being formerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted with all the
other <hi>Lucheſes</hi> his Countrey-men, and adherents to
<hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos</hi> party, becauſe he was his friend, and had for love of
them abandoned altogether the <hi>Toſcan</hi> temper, with ſome hazzard of
being in trouble, he had ſo certainly ſecur'd their fidelity, that there
was no doubt at all but he would return them a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of love
and affection, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all give an account to the Houſe of <hi>Chigi</hi> of
all the inſolencies and grievances offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their female ſex, and to
oblige him to ſatisfie them for all the damages and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts ſuffered
for the ſpace of 12 years under the Papacy, by introducing the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of
<hi>Sodomie,</hi> by reaſon whereof their Trade was utterly deſtroy'd, to
the great prejudice of humane propagation.</p>
            <p>In ſo much as <hi>Nina Barcarola,</hi> who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood very
well how great advantages might accrew to her by the raiſing of the 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104221:7"/>
               <hi>Celſi;</hi> She having the will of <hi>Ravizza</hi> at
command, her obliged ſervant for theſe twenty years, and wherewith ſhe
was alſo aſſured to incline the affection of the ſaid <hi>Celſi</hi>
to any promotion of hers; ſhe did earneſtly endeavour by Language and
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to gain him the Votes of them all, and in in particular of
<hi>Minima Pandolfina, Nina delle Cannaie,</hi> and of <hi>Mary Vittoria delle
Maſſe,</hi> aſſuring them that if they were not wanting in their due
fidelity to concur at her inſtance in the advancement of this perſon, they
ſhould be prodigiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for their pains and affection.</p>
            <p>On the other hand the party of Ladies, who being intereſſed in
their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, take no farther care for the publick good, but only for
themſelves; every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon among them did ſtrongly endeavour to
engage in diſcourſe about their <hi>Inamoratos,</hi> and did abſolutely
op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the pretenſes of the Whores: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon alledging a thouſand
defects againſt <hi>Celſi</hi> and <hi>Spada,</hi> they did pretend that
theſe ſhould be totally excluded as Counterfeits of little credit, and no
indifferency as much with the male as the female ſex; or to ſpeak more
properly, for their applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to both, proteſting that certain
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104221:7"/>was given, that withal they ſeem'd willing to
contradict their own ſatisfaction, and apply themſelves to the wicked
practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Chigi,</hi> yet one of them was her Creature, which was
<hi>Celſi,</hi> and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence ſuſpected to joyn in his Election,
and therefore it was done before the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Erratica,</hi> with the
nomination of <hi>Az<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zolino</hi> or <hi>Maldacchino;</hi> ſhe pretended to be
approved by all the reſt for two reaſons; Firſt, becauſe they being
ſuch perſons, it was expedient in point of policy, that the choice ſhould
light upon ſome youthful perſon, to the end that the length of a good Popes
Reign might give ſome recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for the ſufferings of the diſaſtrous
and villainous Government of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dutches <hi>Mattei,</hi> who was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to loſe her
ſatisfaction and advantage altogether, out of reſpect and civility, did
oppoſe her ſelf, ſaying, that as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of <hi>Celſi</hi>
and of St. <hi>Suſan,</hi> it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary well done; but as to the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of <hi>Azzolino</hi> or <hi>Maldacchino,</hi> ſhe could neither
afford her approbation nor commendation thereunto, becauſe theſe two
perſons being at preſent caſt down low enough in every place, you would
put<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104221:8"/>them in a condition, in the ſpace of few years to
ſcandalize all the Ladies that ever were, and for that reaſon it was not
well nor advantagiouſly done in them to haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard it, having nothing hereafter
to rely upon between the hopes and new fears of being deluded, and to meet with
the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difficulties, from whom they expected immediat aſſiſtance
and happineſs: and that it was moſt credibly related to her, that
<hi>Maldacchino</hi> had a good ſhare of the French Pox by exchange; and if
that as yet the fruits was not maturated, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Thirds were moſt
miſchievous; and therefore there is a neceſſity that we ſhould move
ſlowly in this buſineſs, that we may not be the occaſion of ſo much
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to the univerſality of the female World, and grieve their
conſciences. Whence it appears to me very expedient to beſeech
<hi>Erratica,</hi> that ſhe would be pleaſ'd to give her concurrenr vote
for <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nelli;</hi> who, beſides his being an aged Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ject and a
Relation, he was known to be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good
repute, ſo that he might upon ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rational grounds pretend to this ſuprem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dignity. Beſides he hath given man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proofs of his perſon in
<hi>Spain,</hi> where n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> misfortune
hapned to him, nor was eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104221:8"/>obſerv'd to deviate from the affection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceived by him
of this Sex, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that he had a rough and hairy countenance,
which was the true reaſon that any perſon was compatible, who receiving no
farther information, would have ſworn him to be a moſt cruel
Pentapolitan.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Adrianella</hi> anſwered, your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency by this way
of reaſoning concludes on my ſide, becauſe theſe and many nobler
qualifications do concur in Cardinal <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piglioſi</hi> my friend, an
expert man, well skil'd in the trade, facetious in converſation, of a quick
wit, ingenious in his matter, and very free to acknowledge the ſervices and
the affection of thoſe that moſt reſpect him; beſides his having bin in
<hi>Spain,</hi> and giving far greater teſtimonies than <hi>Bonelli,</hi>
worthy a ſerious reflection; therefore that I being moved with theſe
conſiderations do not condeſcend to their deſires, I beg their pardon,
becauſe I have a great deal of reaſon to ſerve this perſon more then
any other whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Soft a little, my Lady <hi>Adrianella</hi> (replied the Princeſs
of <hi>Roſſano</hi>) and the Lord Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Odelſcalchi,</hi> what
injury hath he done you? you know that we always wiſh't you well, and that my
advantage hath ever been<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104221:9"/>for your good: This Cardinal hath
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved well of our Houſe, and is a perſon that deſerves good will;
and that which is of greateſt importance, he will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to
diſpleaſe me, therefore he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eſteem.</p>
            <p>I beg your Excellencies pardon (<hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella</hi> return'd)
becauſe this is awry-neck't fellow, a mumbler of <hi>Pater noſters,</hi>
that minds not the Ladies; and if by chance he meets one in the Street, he
croſſeth himſelf, as if he ſpied the Devil; and farther, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy let it
ſuffice, that he is a counterfeit Saint. Your Excellency is not ignorant of
the Proverb, <hi>A Butchers dog and Company-keepers, ever avoid,
avoid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Figh, figh, I know he is a man of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and we can meet
with no other, ſaid <hi>Roſſana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adrianella</hi> replied again, if your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency ſhould
talk till to morrow morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I ſhould never be able to underſtand that it
were the part of a judicious perſon to confide in this Pope, who is a
Bleſſing-monger, and hath one fault, that he never looks one in the face;
he is ſo obſtinate, that all the Tortures of <hi>Ripetta</hi> would not at
all move him, although he himſelf be a <hi>Milaneſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104221:9"/>Well Siſter, I ſee there is no
diſcourſing with you, but you wil be paſſionate (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the
Princeſs.)</p>
            <p>With theſe and the like confuſions were things managed for the
enſuing Election; ſo that they ſeem'd to be in ſuch a hurry, that
without a long Seſſion of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, they could not finiſh the
buſineſs of the Election as they had deſign'd, if the death of
<hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould happen, which is much deſir'd.</p>
            <p>Wherefore perceiving on the 22th day that their voices and hopes
did increaſe, by a certain new accident, which, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to report, hapned
to them, they new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awaked out of that ſleep in which they had lien theſe
two dayes without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; every one of them did hold out ſtoutly
for the perſons inſiſted upon: and were by order from the
Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Ladies, and <hi>Angela</hi> only on the behalf of the
Whores, made to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That they ſhould all meet at the
<hi>Vaſchette,</hi> the place appointed for the Conclave, that they might
there make an Aſſembly, and diſcourſe about the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Election,
before they did conclude, that they might with more eaſe and leſs
diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance among them underſtand the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104221:10"/>which it ſeems were now riſen up among them, and that it was known
that they had with publick damage and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity commonly publiſh't the
effecting of their deſires by what they ſaid, contrary to the publick
good.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this ſummons ſeeming very proper and convenient,
there was not ſo much as one perſon that did ſeem averſe to ſo
honorable an undertaking: ſo that on the 22th. day in the place appointed of
the <hi>Vaſchette</hi> near the houſe of <hi>Maria Tereſa,</hi> one of
the Whores of this Company, <hi>ad ſonum Tubi,</hi> (a certain perſon
<hi>John Baptista Gronata</hi> Townclark and Spy to <hi>Don Mario in Borgo</hi>
waited as Bailiff.) The Whores made their ſolemn Entrance, <hi>viz. Angela
Sala</hi> the <hi>Senioreſs, Nina Barcarola, Cicela dello Struzzo, Brigida
della Bufola, Anna</hi> the happy, <hi>Maria Vittoria, Diana Velletrana, Ghita
delle Portiere, Margherita</hi> of <hi>Florence, Minima Pandolfina, Nina
Cucchierina, Nina delle Caniere, Cecca</hi> of <hi>Florence, Niuccia Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccia
del Pancaſcreccio, Nina Faccendona Momma Velletrana, Laura</hi> of
<hi>Ferrara, Laura Maſſa</hi> with the whole Siſterhood, <hi>Giovanni a
Santa Maria in via,</hi> and <hi>Angela Dezza</hi> of <hi>Garaffone,</hi> 24
perſons in all, inveſted with prudence and authority over the
Bawdy-Houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104221:10"/>There came many factious perſons, who took
part with theſe ſame Ladies, as Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Coadjutors in this
ſo great a work; ſo that there aroſe a moſt extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant confuſion
and conteſt at the door: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that coming to blows for their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
they bang'd one another ſo handſomly, that in the concluſion many of them
were ſtrangely and dangerouſly hurt. The Canon Regular <hi>Scotti,</hi> who
to ſerve <hi>Ravizza</hi> went to wait on <hi>Barcarola,</hi> was ſo
wel-favour'dly beaten in this skirmiſh, that he is ſtill much pain'd in the
arms and knees, ſo that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtir out in foul weather.</p>
            <p>The Abbat <hi>Pizziſio</hi> quite loſt his noſe, ſo that
he was forc'd to get him a Taliacotian one.</p>
            <p>The Lord Cardinal <hi>Aquaviva,</hi> who would court <hi>Minima
Pandolfina</hi> for the intereſt of <hi>Azzolino,</hi> did ſo wrench his
back in the conflict, that he hath ſuch an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as by degrees will
turn to the Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the reins.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Ceſarini,</hi> and the Popes two Chancellors, who
endeavour'd to make friends to keep in their office, were ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thraſh'd 't one of them receiv'd a back-blow upon his Privy-members, and the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a blow in his groin, which ſwel'd<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104221:11"/>ſo
grievouſly, that it will be many months in cure.</p>
            <p>But my Lord <hi>Altemps</hi> they ſay receiv'd the greateſt
prejudice of them all, who fell backward on the floor ſo unhappily, that he
brake his head in the fall, and receiv'd the ſame hurt in the groin as the
Chancellor had, by a blow in his fore-parts: ſo that the accidents in
themſelves were very ſad and unexpected.</p>
            <p>The She-Conclaviſts were hereupon at peace, and whilſt they
were complement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, the Ladies came to them; who, neither upon one
conſideration not other, more than out of policy, daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed; laying
aſide all manner of thoughts whatſoever, concerning the inequality and
diſrepute of theſe Curtezans, approached the door in a moſt ſcornful
and unaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom'd way: and having made all the Curtezans ſilly Gallants
ſtand aſide, they paſſing them by, went up of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and
ſo mixed themſelves with the Whores, the men following them.</p>
            <p>It ſeem'd to ſome of the men, that this union of Ladies and
Whores, was a very unequal mixture; ſo that without thinking of it, ſome of
them began to diſcourſe very freely of that buſineſs: and making ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104221:11"/>reflection upon <hi>Erratica,</hi> and gueſſing pretty
nearly what might be the cauſe of it, did very much preſs to know the true
reaſon that obliged Her to give this occaſion of admiration. Wherefore She
giving them to underſtand, That this was occaſion'd by reaſon of the
infrequency of ſuch Meetings: She order'd with a nod, that thoſe that were
aſſembled ſhould come to Her, and that they ſhould leave off their
complements at preſent, and make uſe of them another time, delivering
Herſelf as followeth:</p>
            <q> 
               <p>
                  <hi>THe deplorable condition into which the perfidiouſneſs and
obſtinate averſion of the Seneſes to Ladies, who to this day ſtill
reign, hath involv'd us; is a thing ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and publick: that it ſeems
to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and diſſonant to reaſon, ſo much as to doubt that it
is not very notorious to you: Since that we have daily ſeen for theſe
Twelve years and better hitherto, that the Popes Anticham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are fill'd with
the youths of the Family of the</hi> Chigi, <hi>who to our diſgrace triumph
in that grandeur, which we heretofore ſhould have nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeated, and now being
wanderers and baniſh'd thence, we earneſtly ſeek after; which might
eaſily perſwade you to believe, that we have had a great deal of violence
offer'd us, for which<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104221:12"/>we muſt ſeek out redreſs,
becauſe herein not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our diſparagement, but our prejudice is equal:
ſo that it ſeems your admiration deſerves no excuſe, ſince that being
inform'd of the urgency of the buſineſs, and the neceſſity of the
eaſe, that you ſhould admire at it, is strange, being this very day
conſtrain'd, though to your detriment, to convene, and agree with other
perſons, though inferiour to you in condition, mean in quality, of a
ſtrange fortune, and infamous by profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo much the more, that the
countenancing ſome actions, though unuſual, and otherwiſe not permitted a
Prince; is not altogether blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, when private intereſt, which policy
truſts us to provide for before before our reputation, or any other thing
whatſoever move us to it; beſides, ſince we have ſhewed our ſelves
ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, this appearing ſo diſjoynted, that is, by the Ladies
ſtanding upon preheminence, and not condeſcending to treat with the Whores,
is a conceit that will bring ſo little advantage, or profit to us, that we
are reſolv'd for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to bring up this custom, that as well the
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as the Curtezans ſhall be equally eſteem'd, and without any
imaginable distinction, that</hi> Whore <hi>and</hi> Lady <hi>ſignifies the
ſame thing; to the end, that when a Lady will ſeek her own ſatisfaction,
or a Whore pretend to repreſent a Lady, it ſhall be freely permitted
without<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104221:12"/>meeting with any ſigns of deriſion by the hand
being pointed at, or ſupercilious reproaches, as to this day is uſed in the
City, and we our ſelves did a little before our wonderful
conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore, Gentlemen, reſt ſatisfied with this
Declaration, and leave us free to our ſelves, by your departure, to negotiat
in this buſineſs, for which we did call togither this Aſſembly,</hi>
and ſo ended.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Gentlemen that ſtood by were all ſatisfied with this
<hi>Harangue,</hi> and in token of their conſent, did agree with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
applauſe of <hi>Erattica's</hi> expreſſions, and departed ſatisfied to
underſtand that hence forward they ſhould not need to be inquiſitive
whether a Woman was a Lady or a Whore; ſince it was indifferently concluded
among themſelves, that who names the one excludes not the other; and that
mentioning the one, both the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were expreſſed.</p>
            <p>When the Gentlemen were departed, <hi>Erattica</hi> took up again
her diſcourſe <hi>de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> who continuing ſtill in the ſame mind
ſhe was at firſt, did endeavour to leave no ſtone unturn'd, which might
afford her ſome hope of obtaining her deſires in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of
<hi>Azzolino</hi> and <hi>Maldocchino,</hi> with a<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104221:13"/>deſign
to captivate the minds of all Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers; that they might in the end find
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves oblig'd to ſubſcribe and condeſcend unto her will: She then
proſecuting her diſcourſe, thus ſaid;</p>
            <q> 
               <p>
                  <hi>I believ'd it my duty (Dear Siſters) in this ſo important
juncture of affairs; upon which your advancement or ruine indiſputably
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, to adviſe you of, and diſcover unto you, all that I apprehend may
prove injurious, or elſe advantageous to us in our deſigns, becauſe I
have been a party among you ever ſince I firſt heard our Pope was at
Confesſion. Beſides that, Ladies you ſee the opinions of every one are
ſo tumultuous and diſagreeing concerning theſe matters, that I had
reſolv'd, as a thing almoſt deſperate, to leave off all, and to refer the
ſucceſs of this new Election to the conduct of chance and fortune: But
recollecting my thoughts upon this matter, and remembring the cruel
perſecutions that our Occupation hath been under for ſo many years, and the
great decay thereof in the time of theſe</hi> Seneſes, <hi>theſe modern
ſcandals of the</hi> Brothel-houſe, <hi>and moſt cruel</hi> Diocleſians
<hi>of our natural de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, I have found my ſelf ſo much mov'd with
compaſsion and juſtice; that I could not at least but endeavour to make you
underſtand my thoughts and deſires, which are altogether<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104221:13"/>directed to your profit and ſatisfaction; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you think
that I mind not the dignity of our Sex, or at least that I lay it not to heart,
I ſwear you are deceiv'd in this particular, ſince you could never
diſcern that I ever did you any injury. Therefore believe that it was either
out of pure neceſsity to content thoſe few that remain, which are at this
day reduced to a very inconſiderable number; or becauſe the fear I had of
making our ſecret delights pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and infamous in the eye of the world,
tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath brought me thus
furniſhed with council, from that which I thought not only for my own, but
their reputation alſo.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore I think it convenient to acquaint you, that
reflecting upon all that I have glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon in this particular, you ought to
fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me abſolutely, in the choſing (during this vacancy) for our Pope
one of theſe moſt truſty perſons, either</hi> Azzolino, <hi>or</hi>
Maldacchino, <hi>your moſt affectionate friend, as you know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly by
experience.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p>
                  <hi>And to the end that you may understand I ſhould not have
attempted to propoſe theſe perſons to you, out of a deſire to
aſſume an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power of Election, and perſonate the Queen out of my
own Dominions, without a full aſſurance of your ſatisfaction in, and
advantage by, them.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104221:14"/>
                  <hi>Therefore I do declare and protest, that
if you will concur in the Election of the two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons above-named, they,
before we enter into the Conclave, or at leaſt before we come to a debate
concerning them, ſhall promiſe and ſwear to theſe following
Capitulations.</hi>
               </p> 
               <list>
                  <item>I. The Lord Cardinal <hi>Azzolino</hi> ſhall ſwear that
he will make a Bull, that from the time of his ſitting in the Chair, it may
be lawful for the future for any Prieſt, Fryar, religious Perſon, either
conſtituted or not conſtituted in Eccleſiaſtical Dignities, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to
go a Whoring, without any fear of affronts or diſturbance, either by night or
day, or in any ſeaſon of the year whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</item>
                  <item> II. He ſhall ſet forth a legal Declaration, when he
obtains the Government of the State, that the Ladies that are ſingle, or
married, may without any oppoſition, ſhame or diſparagement, and without
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring any penalty, either of their Prince, Husbands or Parents, indulge
their own humour as much as they pleaſe; nor may they, nor ought they be
obſtructed by any means whatſoever, no more than in their going to
Maſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104221:14"/>III. That neither publick nor private
Ladies may, or ought be compel'd to change their appartment for the lodging of
their Friends, unleſs in the moſt exceſſive heat; that is, from the
25th of <hi>July</hi> to the very end of the 25th of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> upon
pain of being guilty of publick violence, if they are not content, and
voluntarily agree to it; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the firſt, ſecond, and third day, they
lodge in Inns, that Counts and Marqueſſes may happen to lodge in the
ordinary Chambers of their Houſe, upon pain, to the tranſgreſſors
hereof, of his diſpleaſure.</item>
                  <item> IV. That the Canon Regular <hi>Del Corno,</hi> My Lord
<hi>Pepe,</hi> my Lord <hi>Anguiſciola,</hi> my Lord <hi>Cafarelli,</hi> my
Lord <hi>Bernino,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Cavallernio,</hi> and all the generation
of the <hi>Seneſes,</hi> even to the laſt man of them, ſhall be remov'd
far from the City and the bounds thereof; to the end that they may not infuſe
into the minds of the people, by their heretical doctrines concerning poor
Ladies, that perſwaſion, that they ought to be abhorr'd and avoided, as
they have already begun, and we have ſeen practiſed to this very
day.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104221:15"/>V. And finally he ſhall impoſe a
great Tax upon thoſe that keep Pages; which, to tell you the truth Siſters,
are our utter ruine, for ſince the vicinity of that odor is in the noſtrils
of Men, the Chamber-maids and Matrons are neglected, and are not thought
perſons fit for any other ſervice, but of this nature; and therefore I have
diſcovered the larger extent of the uſe of thoſe Chamber-fellows,
<hi>Valets de Chambre,</hi> youths in the Shops, and Barbers boys; by whoſe
means the whole world ſeems to be altogether ſtrangers to us, as we plainly
ſee.</item>
               </list> 
               <p>Therefore, Siſters, to tell you the truth, if you accept of this
offer in good part which this perſon makes you, a man of himſelf faithful
and rational, you will find that he cannot poſſibly be bettered, as for our
uſe: and now to weigh well the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of theſe ſame
Capitulations, you will apprehend there can be no other way or means found more
proper to bring the Brothel-houſe to its antient Cuſtom, in ſpight of
that curſed practice of the <hi>Seneſes,</hi> then what is therein ſet
down; beſides, the moſt pregnant circumſtances that reſult 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104221:15"/>from this particular for the liberty of the Ladies, who, to
this very day, are forced to run through a thouſand dangers, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
means, and infinite troubles; then they may without any imputation or
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency, take a fuller and freer ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in all things; a thing,
which to ſpeak truth, would be of ſufficiency, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of any
other; to ſtir up any Perſon whatſoever among us to proceed with
expedition to ſo honourable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved an Election.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi>If then your fancy ſhould waver upon this conſideration,
that he is ſo affectionatly and really mine, that you cannot agree to this
Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then I return and adviſe you with all clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and
ſincerity, for the great advantage of all your Conſiſtory, however do not
ſuffer your ſelves to be depriv'd of imagination and ſenſe, but being
guided by reaſon, reſolve at leaſt that</hi> Maldacchino <hi>wall be the
perſon, who I am confident will have ſucceſs in all his undertakings, to
his profit, honour and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. O but you will ſay, what will the
world think, if we ſhould reſolve to make this perſon Pope? one that is a
beast ſo bruitiſh, hath a look ſo deformed, a countenance ſo rude, a
ſhape ſo il-proportion'd. Laugh in your ſleeve at them, and make this
anſwer to convince any<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104221:16"/>perſon that talks to you
concerning him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do but mind what he hath; and do not go about to
ſeek better bread then is made of Wheat. If they ſhould chance to ſay
that he is a witleſs mad-fellow, he commits nothing but abſurdities, he
never entertains a thought but what is folly in the very abſtract, he never
ſpeaks but he manifeſts his ſimplicity; it is no matter for that, let
them go on, and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you pleaſe to give them any reply, tell them,
that we have no need of</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>nor Cicero's, but of lazy idle
perſons, and</hi> Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma-luques, <hi>to lead them by the noſe as we
pleaſe, and that will be ſubſervient to our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour night and day, and
beſtow what they have upon us without many words and diſcourſe; and that
which is of greateſt moment, that they be not ſo nice, but that they can
eat the bread of their own Table, and ſatiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therewith,
without going about to ſeek other Junkets, as thoſe learned men uſe to
do. And you know very well, that in the long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of your
profeſſion, you ever met with thoſe that are moſt curious, and nice to
be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with here and there one, who pretend to walk on tiptoe, and to
ſpeak mincingly. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in this perſon you will meet with nothing but
affibility, kindneſs, a readineſs to ſerve you, and pleaſe your humour:
There is no danger<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104221:16"/>that he will be much inclin'd to
ſuſpicion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect or reſpect; with a good meaning will do what
ever you ſhall deſire him, and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain no other thought but how to
pleaſe and content you; and, nay further, that you may in ſhort know, and
conſider of what nature his proffers are, he ſhall alſo capitulate with
you, as followeth.</hi>
               </p> 
               <list>
                  <item>I. He will make you ſhare in his Truſt, and you ſhall
be Miſtreſſes, and ſet foot in any part of the Palace that ſeems
beſt to you, or pleaſeth you moſt, to converſe with him; ſhall call
in the Proclamation againſt Coaches, ſhall free you from the Impoſts at
<hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Chriſtmas;</hi> and (which is of greater
conſequence) will give you alſo leave to keep a <hi>Carneval</hi> in Lent,
and, if occaſion be, will lend his Rochet and Robes, and will go in womans
Apparel like you, and will make as many Banquets as you ſhall think
convenient, without diſturbance, as others do, alwayes keeping himſelf in
that natural and free loving hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of his.</item>
                  <item> II. He ſhall make a moſt ſevere Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
againſt the Uſurers, and build near<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104221:17"/>to St.
<hi>James</hi>'s (the Hoſpital of thoſe that are incurable) an Appartment
for poor baſhful Females, where they ſhall be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with decency and
order, after a noble manner, without being beholding to the ſervice of ſome
contemptible Servant-maid or lewd Fellow, who is very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and when his
aſſiſtance is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, ſhews you a fair pair of heels, and
leaves you to your prejudice.</item>
                  <item> III. He ſhall bring this Cuſtom, which the Civil Offices
of the City yet conſtitute among us, and ſhall appoint you to have
<hi>Praeſidentes</hi> of the Exchequer, Signet-Office and Treaſury, as to
our own intereſts, who ſhall aſſiſt you ſo, that you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
in all junctures of affairs againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies of thoſe Prieſts
and Prelats, who, when they come to take a heat, promiſe great matters, and
when they are once gone, if they have not ſome pretty little youth, who very
gracefully and publickly goes to viſit them again, and to ſollicit them for
their ſervice, there is no profit at all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crews thereby.</item>
                  <item> IV. And finally, he promiſeth to do all that in him lies,
to endeavour to bring them to<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104221:17"/>allow this Cuſtom in the
Conſiſtory, that Popes ſhall Marry, or at leaſt ſhall be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by
the Ladies, to take off that ſcandal, that the Papacy was ever compoſ'd of
ſuch perſons as never fancied any ſuch thing, and that one day it will
come to paſs to our great honour, to have young Popes, and to bring them up
with Pap; that then when they grow up in years, their inclination may wholly
oblige them to us and our ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And to ſum up all, we ſhall have
a Pope, whom if we would have him made on purpoſe, we could not have him
better; as for the reſt, you may rather fear the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>Luigi,</hi> then
him; becauſe he is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without gall, and a great Epicure; and though
he be deformed, yet he is like thoſe Pears in <hi>Rome, that the worſe they
are to ſight, the better they are to eat;</hi> therefore I beg of you to take
theſe reaſons into your ſerious conſideration, and to agree with me in
my opinion for the Election of one of theſe two perſons.</item>
               </list> 
            </q>
            <p>When <hi>Erratica</hi> had concluded her diſcourſe,
<hi>Adrianella</hi> aroſe firſt of all, and with a moderate ſmiling
countenance, making her obeiſance comelily, graciouſly, yet humbly to them
all round, began to make a Speech.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104221:18"/>May it pleaſe your Majeſty to grant me the
favour to be the firſt that ſhall give you my reaſons,; to the end this
noble Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, which apprehend the buſineſs quite contrary to the
ſenſe of your Majeſty, might be able to judge as ſhall ſeem meet to
their ſolid, but womaniſh judgment.</p>
            <p>It is true, nay moſt certainly true, that our ſex hath juſt
reaſon to expect all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that till now could ever have been
deſir'd by us, and which your Majeſty hath ſo Rhetorically deſcribed
and amplified, by the promotion of the two perſons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd: But,
becauſe in ſhort, theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, that are pretended to be agreed
unto by theſe Lords in our ſervice, are more directly for the advantage of
the Publick, then we private Ladies, who paſs for chaſt perſons, under
the title of Ladies, with all the exactneſs we can: Now, to bring us to
conſent to the promotion of theſe perſons for the Publick, and abandon
our particular good, does not ſure with my temper. I having great regard to
that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, that permits not any perſon to leave his own real, for a
titular right: Beſides, to tell you plainly, this confuſion that will
happen in attempting to unite the Ladies and Whores together, without making
any<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104221:18"/>kind of diſtinction or difference; it is true, is a
thing that will be of advantage to thoſe other inconſiderable Ladies, but
will not do me any ſervice at all, but rather an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe then I
loſe all my trouble and care that I have taken all my life-time to be
eſteem'd as a Lady, if I ſhall not be ſo; and to be beleev'd honeſt, if
I am not ſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, therefore I cannot by any means reſt upon thoſe
your ſentiments: And beſides, to deprive my ſelf of the protection of
<hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piglioſi,</hi> my very great and affectionate friend, by whom I and
all the reſt of the Ladies may be well treated, beyond all other perſons:
And indeed, let this be true, what is it to me if the <hi>Florentine</hi>
Faction, or that of <hi>Siena,</hi> hath ſo baſely clouded the glory and
eſteem of our ſex; if I, nevertheleſs, have now at laſt given over my
Trade, and I (for ſome other reaſons) a great while ago have voluntarily
turn'd my back upon my friends, that I might not nauſeate them at the ſight
of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which is altogether ſhort of the voice for dilicacy.</p>
            <p>What need I care if there be a publick Law made concerning the
legallity or il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legallity of Cardinals, Prelats, and all other
Eccleſiaſticks, going without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104221:19"/>to the houſe of
every Lady of theirs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have had,
and ſtill have my houſe full o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
them? Have not you your ſelf, Madam, conſtantly ſeen Cardinal
<hi>Chigi</hi> though a <hi>Seneſe;</hi> Cardinal <hi>Albici,</hi> Cardinal
<hi>Bonviſi, Don Mario, Don Augoſtino,</hi> all thoſe that belong to the
Popes Treaſury and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: and in ſum our greateſt Adverſaries, night
and day, and at all times? Yes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly.</p>
            <p>Then what benefit can I have by this new Order? O! But you will
ſay, they came not to you for your ſake, nor for the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, but for
love of the Eunuchs, that you have gathered together; and therefore it being
not your Trade, it fares with you, as it doth with all Arts; and particularly
that of Cookery, who neither ſpeak, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, nor come to the Cook for
the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, but for his viands. Very good, yet Siſters, every one
helps himſelf with his own, and labors for his own intereſt; becauſe this
world was not made for fools, to ſpeak as I ought.</p>
            <p>So alſo as to other matters concerning Uſurers, St.
<hi>James</hi>'s and <hi>Offices,</hi> though I have paid the Baker, I have not
pawn'd my Cloaths for it: and to tell you true I am in good health, and my
reins are ſtill<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104221:19"/>ſufficiently warm, ſo that I ſhould
want nothing but a little Ambition and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and this I can neither
pretend to, nor hope for, unleſs it be by means of my Lord Cardinal
<hi>Roſpiglioſi.</hi> Therefore her Majeſty may be pleaſ'd to pardon
me, that I cannot poſſibly condeſcend to hers, nor be removed from my own
now ſettled opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Nay, nay, Madam (replied <hi>la Barcarola</hi> to this
diſcourſe) I hope you will not deal thus by us, then your thoughts are only
for your own profit, and do not in the leaſt concern your ſelf for the
Company; be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and fly not out into paſſion; for I deal truly with
you, you are a brave Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezan; and I muſt tell you, that your deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with
thoſe Lords have made you Miſtriſs of your Art, more than any thing
elſe whatſoever: But underſtand how this came to paſs.</p>
            <p>I do proteſt, ſaid <hi>Leonora</hi> preſently, being red
with anger, that what I ſaid, I ſpake not as to you, nor your Company,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I now know you have agreed; but I mention'd it for the other Ladies,
to whom, in my opinion, the ſame reaſons belong, that are ſuitable to the
caſe: as to what remains, now I have declar'd<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104221:20"/>my thoughts,
I will not repent me of it.</p>
            <p>Your Ladiſhips (replied the other) are at the height of your
fortune, and take your reſt at pleaſure, according to the Proverb; you
think that I was, and am yet in ſuch a condition, that I ſtand in need of
no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and if I have not car'd to play the mar-Trade, as ſome others
have done, and to make a medley of Ladies and Whores, yet I have by all means
had, nevertheleſs, Gentlemen and Cardinals, that did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually court me;
nor did I ever much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern my ſelf to be taken notice of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly more
then other perſons, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the courteſies which I could wiſh
for. It is ſufficient that we meet not here to contend about that. The
buſineſs is this, if I can promote my Lord Cardinal <hi>Celſi,</hi> who I
know wiſheth me well, and others as well as he, I underſtand there is
nothing done but what comes through the hands of <hi>Ravizza,</hi> who is
entirely mine, and that I made him what he is; and if he be not ſo with all
perſons, yet he is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithful to me; yet if her Majeſty thinks it
better for the publick good, that this man ſhould be excluded: I will not be
obſtinate in a thing that can no ways prove<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104221:20"/>advantageous
to me; but I am content to give my vote and voice for one of thoſe two
propoſed by her Majeſty, with thoſe capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations mention'd to you;
becauſe I judge it convenient for me ſo to do.</p>
            <p>And I know very well (ſaid <hi>Leonora</hi> ſmiling, and
ſpeaking between the teeth) this is to make a virtue of neceſſity, and to
make uſe of the opportunity to throw off that burthen, which I cannot do,
that the Lady <hi>Nina,</hi> fore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
knows that to believe either <hi>Celſi</hi> or <hi>Ravizzo,</hi> who are a
couple of Traytors, whoſe credit or word are not to be relied upon, who have
a hand in every thing, is to throw her ſelf down a precipice, and to put out
both her eyes; now ſhe goes about to ſeek mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wayes to free her from
the engagement, and to diſoblige her ſelf with the greateſt reputation
imaginable. Alas, Madam <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> take notice, that we know all this. And
what do you know, Madam <hi>Leonora</hi> (<hi>Nina</hi> anſwered) O, I know
(replied the other) that <hi>Celſi</hi> deſir'd ſomething, I know not
what, of you, that you at firſt denied him, and he went to obtain of the Lady
<hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and ſhe ſuddenly granted it him to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight you, without any great
difficulty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou were extreamly
galled, when you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſtood
it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:104221:21"/>
               <hi>Minima</hi> replied, I hope you will
excuſe me, Madam <hi>Leonora,</hi> it was not abſolutely ſo; becauſe
that if it be true, that I ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his deſire, yet it is not altogether
that I condeſcended to it to croſs the Lady <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> but becauſe
<hi>Ravizza</hi> adviſ'd me to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour him, he being in a capacity to be
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſerviceable to me; and the more, becauſe he was in credit and
hopes to be advanced to the Papacy, therefore I was his ſervant.</p>
            <p>So then, was <hi>Ravizza</hi> the man that gave you this
counſel? Alas poor Lady <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> (replied <hi>Nina.</hi>) Truly
(anſwered <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi>) thoſe that are ſo, I tell you true, it was
juſt as the Lady <hi>Leonora</hi> ſaid; you muſt underſtand I was ever
of a free temper, and clearly diſcover my thoughts; I muſt be plain with
you; do you not know why you had no notice? The reaſon was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that
it being publickly known, that you play the man more then the woman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
beſides you get together all the young boys of the City, to trade with the
<hi>Seneſes,</hi> to the great damage and prejudice of the reſt of our
Order; inſtead of being regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the liſt of thoſe of the
<hi>Vaſchette,</hi> you are found in the roll of the <hi>Piazza Nova<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na:</hi>
Therefore we need not wrangle, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104221:21"/>make any more ado, but to tell you the truth, and
modeſtly paſs it by, and not do as thoſe people that have their horns in
their pocket, and yet will faſten them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their head whether you will or
no.</p>
            <p>How (ſaid <hi>Nina</hi>) doth your Excellency ſay, that I keep
a company of young boys in my houſe, and that they are intol'd in the
<hi>Piazza Novana?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay (replied the Princeſs) that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons know you take
delight in nothing but ſuch unlawful actions: nay farther, that once
ſpeaking of me, you ſaid, whilſt they were talking, that <hi>Don
Camillo</hi> my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would never be kind to me more, that he griev'd to
ſee the inſupportable extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie of my family, and therefore he did
miſ-uſe me, and forſook my bed thereupon; and this befell me, becauſe I
could not be content with that moderation, which you uſ'd to preſerve your
friends; which was to keep every inconſiderable complaint to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to his knowledge, and ſo to
cover <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he natural faults, and
conſtantly bear with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he uſual
changes that happen in the world.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that I had ſaid ſo, though real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y I don't remember that I ever troubled
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſelf with other perſons
concerns; what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed the Eagle care
for flies? How comes<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104221:22"/>it to paſs (ſaid <hi>Nina</hi>)
that this Trade, as well as that of trafficking in the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of other
perſons, crept into my Houſe. Alas, Siſter (replied the Princeſs, you
muſt not engage people to ſell all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that when they are forced to
it, they ſay more then is convenient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nina</hi> made anſwer, ſay as much as you think
convenient, what you pleaſe, I would know, whatſoever it coſt me, whether
thoſe things are true or falſe, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of me. Then you have a
deſire I ſhould tell you, well, I will, though it be but to ſpight you
(replied the Princeſs). Do you not believe that it is not known all over
<hi>Rome,</hi> that you made a conſpiracy againſt all the reſt of your
poor Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to procure their ruine, without any hope of recovery, if they
did not diſpoſe themſelves very circumſpectly to take all things in
their order? Do you thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Rome</hi> is ignorant of your agreement wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fulvio Zacconato,</hi> now Heir, and the Lord <hi>del Medico
Miſſorio</hi> (though ſome think h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is his Baſtard) who is now cal'd the Abbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Miſſorio,</hi> to make a Conventicle of
<hi>Seneſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> both at home and abroad, and ſo root ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Commandres of the
<hi>Brothel-houſe,</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
patent of Whore of the Palace; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104221:22"/>then what wonder was it, if all was fiſh that came to the
Net: and the concourſe of all the Nobility which you had, was becauſe who
ever came had his Coach. And now, my Daughter, things at <hi>Rome</hi> are
ſoon known; and a bleſſing upon the Knight <hi>Ciarci,</hi> with the good
memory of the Earl of <hi>Gaddi Delci,</hi> who were the moſt infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and
beggerly raſcally Knights that ever were, and came to <hi>Rome</hi> that
night, by all means, when you had broken open the back-door when they cur'd you
of thoſe ill thoughts, and ſtopt the courſe of your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed career, that
you had undertaken; and if this man be dear to you ſtill (as is believ'd)
although that <hi>Miſſorio</hi> knows yet how to keep up the good opinion
of Cardinal <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> and his Eminencie <hi>Chigi,</hi> nevertheleſs
the thing is but ſhort liv'd; becauſe I am now inform'd, that the Houſe
of the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barini</hi> begins to perſecute it, without any hopes of
hinderance whatſoever, which they go about with all diligence to do; and
Madam <hi>Roſſa,</hi> the fair ſpoken, goes about inſtructing them:
'tis a madneſs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it, Siſter, becauſe that the Lettice
and Artichoks, when they are grown ſeedy, are food for poor people, and not
for the Nobility. Now, Siſter, what ſay you, and<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104221:23"/>ſhall
I ſay more to you? Do as I do, do; content your ſelf to go about your own
bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, that will be better for you: Know this, that the Proverb
ſaith, that <hi>whoſoever comes to a wedding without invitation, either is
a fool, or a madman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The unfortunate <hi>Stagnarina</hi> was in ſuch an amazement,
that beſides her being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally of a low ſtature, ſhe became now ſo
little that ſhe could creep into an augur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole, and ſo being quite jear'd
out of her skin, and deluded, went away without taking leave of the
company.</p>
            <p>Now the tumult being allay'd by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of this
fantaſtical baggage, they return'd to their firſt work, though it was late;
and it did ſeem that the Concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſts were tir'd out from evermore
diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in that place, becauſe ſome of them did make a ſign, as
if they would make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who ſaid, that their heads ached through the
exceſſive heat; and others mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and ſaid they were thirſty, and
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like; inſomuch that it look't
as if it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been a Jewiſh
Synagogue. But <hi>la Roſſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who griev'd, and ſaw well this hurly-bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, was
diſpleaſ'd that ſhe was diſturb'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by that draggle-tail'd Slut, being the Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſtory was ſo
attentive to what ſhe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104221:23"/>prepar'd to ſay concerning <hi>Odeſcalco:</hi>
Wherefore <hi>Erratica</hi> underſtanding it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſay, for God's
ſake, Ladies, let not our buſineſs be turn'd into diſcourſe of toys
and trifles; and that they would take the weight of the affair into their
conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for the moſt pertinent reaſons that did now concur; and
if there was any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to mention any thing elſe, they ſhould ſpeak
it freely, that it ſhould be carried on without diſcompoſing the
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and if agreeing in their opinion, they were not as yet reſolv'd to
bring their votes to a head, they might, upon the firſt notice given of the
Chair being vacant, come thither, and include thoſe perſons they moſt
deſir'd.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Roſſana</hi> began to talk high, and with a look
neither ſupercilious nor pleaſant, but between both; what will your
Majeſty then forget the Cardinal <hi>Odeſcalco,</hi> your moſt
affectionate Servant, and friend to my Houſe? Is it poſſible, that the
merit of this perſon doth not neceſſarily urge you to ſhake off all
other perſons, to follow him ſingle, and particularly his favours above the
reſt.</p>
            <p>So honeſt a man, a perſon of ſo clear a ſpirit, a mind
ſo adorned with virtues; O,<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104221:24"/>Madam, Methinks you do him
wrong, and and that your Majeſty falls ſhort of your devoir, and your
ſolid judgment. Your Majeſty, I hope, will pardon me for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo
boldly in this Aſſembly. In fine then, Juſtice muſt take place.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I beſeech your Majeſty once again to take this
buſineſs into due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that I may at leaſt reap this
ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as to be ſatisfied with the refuſal, that your Majeſty
and the reſt of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies can make.</p>
            <p>Very well; yet not ſo well as may ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Excellency
neither (replied <hi>Brigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daccia</hi>) I know that we ſhall have but cold
entertainment from this hypocritical Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite; I beſeech you, Princeſs,
tell me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will your Excellency ſwear that this man will diligently
mind the Ladies buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>verbi gratia,</hi> that he will be pleaſed
to converſe with them, and be kind unto them?</p>
            <p>I can tell you a truth, (replied the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs) that he hath
viſited me often at my habitation, and behav'd himſelf with all the
affibility imaginable, and I could not perceive any natural averſion that he
had for buſineſſes of that nature. Yes (ſaid <hi>Brigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daccia</hi>) and
pray how long ſince was it that<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104221:24"/>theſe amourous
confidential viſits paſſed between you? By my life, if you have no other
commodities but ſuch as theſe to carry to Market, you muſt even ſet it
off with fair words, for there are no things to ſet a price on it.</p>
            <p>We have been here all this day, and yet have done nothing to
conclude: the Lady <hi>Nuccia Bellaccia</hi> began to ſpeak, the Lady
<hi>Nuccia delle canuccie</hi> accompanying with a 'tis very true, Lady: The
firſt went on, and ſaid, Their Ladiſhips do not know what is come into my
mind; that this Pope being to be made by force, and not being able to avoid any
other Election, it would be well for the future to let theſe Cardinals
continue a while, with a venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to them; becauſe they being Prieſts, we
ſhall agree very badly with their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and that we ſhould make choice
of ſome good Fryar or Monck, as it was of old; and thoſe (as I have heard
my Grandmother ſay) were happy dayes, that the Ladies had more double
Ducatoons then; and the Bawdy-houſes were far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter furniſhed with moneys
then ever as the Treaſury of <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, my Daughters, ſaid <hi>Angela Sala,</hi> it is a madneſs to
think of it; for beſides, that<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104221:25"/>this thing you talk of
cannot be, it were requiſit you ſhould underſtand one thing, that now the
Fryars have made a Cuſtom; beſides that, which is known to be done to
Novices, there once came a buſineſs to my hands that did aſtoniſh me,
and <hi>Maria Vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria</hi> knows it very well too; how I was treated by a
certain Fryar, who was going to Supper the Thurſday before
<hi>Shrove-Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the laſt year.</p>
            <p>I thank God I was never driven to that diſgrace (replied
<hi>Nuccia.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Said the <hi>Seinoreſs,</hi> becauſe you have had
<hi>Timone,</hi> who was a French-man: But as to the Lady <hi>Nina,</hi> to
tell you the truth, I cannot underſtand it, by reaſon the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
between her and <hi>Silvio de Vecchi,</hi> who is of <hi>Siena,</hi> proves the
contrary.</p>
            <p>Indeed, indeed (the Lady began to reply all in a heat) if you by
chance had at any time talk't with me of any ſuch thing, and I would have
ſhut the doors againſt him with diſdain.</p>
            <p>I but (the old Lady rejoyn'd) and what did <hi>Nicholas
Lacche</hi> do there about a year ago, as you love him, tell me?</p>
            <p>It is three years ago, ſaving the truth (the other return'd
anſwer.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104221:25"/>Is it but three years (replied
<hi>Brigidaccia</hi>) ſince his Son the Duke of <hi>Carpinetto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princeſs made anſwer, it was now twenty years ago.</p>
            <p>Go to, Your Excellency never asks me any other queſtions. I know
that I can at preſent ſwear that ſhe is deceiv'd, becauſe the viſits
were not hers, nor did the Lord Cardinal give himſelf that trouble for her
ſake; I am ſure of that.</p>
            <p>And you, to ſpeak true (replied the Dutcheſs <hi>Mattei</hi>)
ſeeing that he never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeth with Chriſtians, that he is ſo
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in his chymerical fancies, that he pretends to be ſo good and
lively a Saint, and then to do all things after his own way, as if no other
perſon in the world had brains beſides himſelf: To deal plainly with your
Excellency, this is enough to make us ſo far from deſiring to choſe him
Pope, as that he ſhould not be ſo much as a Parochian in <hi>Rome.</hi> I
beſeech you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that if we ſhould by chance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon this
Election, the Papacy would be all French (though he be a <hi>Milaneſe,</hi>
and ſo conſequently ought to be a Spaniard) and nothing of Italian among
them; beſides, we know that this humour is not conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended unto, unleſs
it be to promote<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104221:26"/>Scullery-boys and Oſtlers, all
<hi>France</hi> and <hi>Lorrain</hi> would leave their habitations to come to
<hi>Rome;</hi> one to be made a Canon Regular, another an Abbat, one a
Biſhop, and the other a Cardinal. Doth not your Excellency ſee that there
appear none but ordinary perſons in the Anti-Chamber, and Gentlemen of the
third degree? But pray let us forbear, and diſgrace our ſelves no farther
with diſcourſing any more of him, becauſe it is a thing beſide the
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Beſides the matter, I, moſt extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily (all the
followers of <hi>Nina Barcarola</hi> began to ſay) and at the worſt it
would be better in caſe of neceſſity, to conclude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Spadino,</hi>
or <hi>Celſi;</hi> is it not true, Madam <hi>Angela?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, Madam (She anſwered) and I, as for my part, will be of the
ſame opinion: And therefore I am content to follow her Majeſty to the
uttermoſt, to include one of thoſe ſhe hath mentioned; as for the reſt,
I will not quit my own, ſince others will not do ſo neither.</p>
            <p>My Siſters, of all theſe three Hero's, the <hi>Crab,</hi> at
beſt, would (ſaid She) that took the <hi>Wolfe,</hi> they are Husband-men
without government, and court you moſt;<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104221:26"/>and, according to
the notes of their <hi>Sol fa,</hi> they will keep time with 39, and it may be
more.</p>
            <p>Will you, in fine, have me make it out clearly to you; they are
neither good for men nor women; and for forrain affairs, two of them are of the
nature of a Roman, and the laſt is a perfidious Teatine. What can be ſaid
more? 'tis a Triumvirate, that will make Sugar-ſops for the Devil when he is
ſick. I, for my part, had rather Father <hi>Carovila</hi> ſhould be Pope,
if he could riſe again from the dead, then one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Erratica</hi> began to expreſs her ſelf thus; no more of
this diſcourſe; this is no place appointed for Devils; and ſince we
ſee, that we cannot all this day diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch this buſineſs, it is
ſufficient that we have brought it to that paſs, that we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the
difficulty: As for what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, the beſt courſe we can take will be to
make an end with that Directrix, Time and Opportunity. I am ſatisfi'd that
they underſtand the advantages, that thoſe perſons I mention'd,
propoſ'd to them; and I take no farther care for the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>La Leonora,</hi> that was ſo long without ſpeaking,
ſeeing things more intricate then<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104221:27"/>ever, began to hope
ſhe ſhould have time to negotiate, and like one, who among the reſt, was
perhaps the moſt crafty, and beſt known in the humors of the world, had it
in her head, raiſed her ſelf to ſay three or four Countrey ſongs, to
diſmiſs the Aſſembly, and move <hi>Erratica</hi> a little to anger,
that was a little too much ſatisfied that ſhe had gain'd the major part of
their Votes on her ſide at the firſt: Wherefore turning to her; in truth,
even as your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty can with ſo much eaſe obtain the good will of all,
for the promotion of thoſe perſons you propoſe to St. <hi>Peter's</hi>
Chair; ſo I believe you may obtain your deſire in making your ſelf be
choſen Pope, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of difficulty, becauſe no perſon would
deny you their vote.</p>
            <p>Without doubt (<hi>Brigidaccia</hi> anſwered nimbly, and if it
were not to her diſgrace, that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> had, who is of ſo
ſtrange a temper, the buſineſs would be done; becauſe, I believe, that
he had a mind to make <hi>Erratica</hi> one among the men, ſince it was not
his deſign to place her among the Beaſts. But patience, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, for he is
as much a Merchant that loſeth, as he that wins.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104221:27"/>Now they all were up to return home to their
Houſes, the ſecond meeting being appointed to be the next week, when the
Lord <hi>Stecchino,</hi> Prince of the Brothel-houſe, was ſeen coming into
the Conclave, who being very much troubled and afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, laying his hand upon
his head, and making his honour in faſhion of a half-moon, with his
Bandy-legs, began, with a thouſand ſighs, in the midſt of the
Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, being almoſt drowned in a torrent of tears, to howle out in
this manner: O miſerable wretches that we are! We are undone, we are ruin'd:
O the diſgrace of Nature! O curſed influence of the Stars! The Pope
recovers, the Pope proves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better.</p>
            <p>You would have thought the ſoul was departing from theſe
wretched people at the hearing of this voice, and that their ſpirit was
vaniſhing; inſomuch, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many, you could ſcarce find one
that could do ſo much as draw out theſe words, though with great trouble,
though they knew not in the leaſt how the buſineſs went: O, how goes
affairs, my Lord <hi>Stec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chino?</hi> How did you come to know this? Very ill
(anſwered <hi>Stecchino.</hi>) You know the Pope was given over, if the
Relation be<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104221:28"/>true, that there being a ſtone looſned in
his bladder, it hindred his Urine, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that he began now to exceed the
time allotted by the Phyſitians to his life, that ſuffers ſuch accidents:
Whereupon the world being turn'd into a general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, there was not a
voice, but what did raiſe it ſelf up to beg of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be careful of
this ſo jovial and much deſir'd termination; and there was not a heart,
that did not offer up its deſires to the benignity of deſtiny, that this
infamous Sodomit might yield to Fate. Therefore I, who among the reſt, was
moſt ſollicitous and moſt curious for our own common intereſt, did by
many pretenſes get into the Palace, and ſo far within the Appartments,
without giving, or taking exceptions from any perſons, I underſtood all the
novelties whatſoever that paſſed, they being all in ſuch a peck of
troubles: And in fine, I came to know this, and that ſo certain, that I
wanted time to come away, and acquaint you with the news; (it being
aſſur'd) of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon felicity, when unexpectedly, behold, I perceiv'd a
ſuddain change, which ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extraordinary joy among thoſe mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
caſt me down into the Aybſs of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104221:28"/>Having received this information, the
Conſiſtory brake up with a ſhower of tears, and lamentations; ſome of
them blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the Deſtinies for their perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and others
againſt the impiety of Heaven it ſelf; they went down the Stairs muttering,
that it look't juſt as if Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day had been come; and with much ado there
was one; I know not what curious perſon, who cryed aloud at the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold
of the door; Make an end of your ſtory <hi>Stecchini;</hi> tell us how it
was; and he anſwered,</p>
            <p>I have told you how the buſineſs went already; He can Piſs
now, and we may go—if we will.</p>
            <p>When the Aſſembly was departed from the place, and every one
accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by her Gallant to her lodgings, who waited for her at the door; an
Officer of one of the Juſtices of the Peace came in to take a view of the
places where they ſate, that he might be able to give an account to him that
had commanded him ſo to do, of the order of precedency which was obſerv'd
among them. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was
impoſſible to ſtay there long, ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trong was the ill ſcent that they
had left behind them; Beſides ſome pieces of<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104221:29"/>Purple were
ſpi'd upon the floor, which made the Officer go out, crying, Boys, Boys, What
do we do with ſo many Whores?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104221:29"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE Between <hi>Paſquin</hi> and <hi>Marforio,</hi>
Upon the ſame Subject of WHOREDOM</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</speaker>
               <p>DEar Friend, O how I am over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to ſee thee in ſuch good
health; and that which is of greater importance, altogether lively and well
diſpoſ'd; but what novelty mov'd you, what motive did drive you into
theſe parts? what curioſity obliged you to my Quarters, now the ſeaſon
is ſo exceſſive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot, to the
great hazzard of your perſon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104221:30"/>
               <speaker>Marforio,</speaker>
               <p>Truly, if ever I had reaſon to pay you my devoir, I judge I
ought to do it now; for at this preſent, I do not only ſatisfie my own
ſelf, but give the world to underſtand how I eſteem your
Friendſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Soft and fair a little; let us in part wave theſe ceremonies,
leaſt we make the Court laugh at us; for to deal cordial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you as a
friend, they will all flout at us, if we our ſelves uſe thoſe
ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which we diſcommend in other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Speak freely, you have
ſomewhat to ſay to me, is not that true? Do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal your thoughts from
me, let me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them exactly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marf.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs my ſelf overcome, and therefore I declare
ſincerely to you, that a deſire of being ſatisfied in mind, and not
ſuperficial complements, forced me with ſuch ſpeed to viſit you at your
habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>Aſſure your ſelf, that as ſoon as I ſaw you ſet your
foot within the door, I did imagine you were diſcontented in mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
I'le lay what you will, that I know th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe of all this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I'le lay no wager, 'tis beneath a Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpirit; and you would win as ſurely, as ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> certain few of the Popes Subjects are
ſav'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104221:30"/>I come hither to be inform'd by you of the
ſtate of the intereſts of our Curtezans, and of the iſſue of their
Conclave, held with ſuch exquiſite order, and great diligence, endeavouring
to get the knack of molding a Pope of their own faſhion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Very well, the mind then of the Roman is loſt and not gain'd
by me; for I beleev'd as an article of my Creed (but ſuch a Creed as is
chewed in <hi>Rome</hi>) that it was a buſineſs of greater importance then
what you relate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Of greater importance? you drol with me: there is no other
diſcourſe at Court but of this Curtezan Conclave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>I know it; but we ought to have an eye upon more ſubſtantial
and profound matters then theſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>More ſubſtantial, I grant you, but more profound, I deny:
Becauſe when we ſpeak of the Whores of <hi>Rome,</hi> the diſcourſe is
of a moſt profound thing; they being more unfathomable then the Sea;
inſomuch that the moſt ſubtile Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians, that from time to time
fiſh for their Science in this Ocean, cannot find out the bottom with the
help of all their Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical matter: Well, 'tis true that at preſent, the
Whores of <hi>Rome</hi> are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104221:31"/>now a days,
but for their profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, whilſt one good pound of a villain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bull-Galf
is judg'd more ſubſtantial for a Roman, and for the preſervation of the
health of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> then twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the beſt young Heifers.
But to ſay true, in my opinion, to diſcourſe of the Curtezans of
<hi>Rome,</hi> is a ſubject ſubſtantial enough; ſince they are full
(though there be always a place empty, which the more it is repleniſhed the
emptier it grows) of the Subſtance both of the one and other; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
of Eccleſiaſtical ſubſtance, which nouriſheth the moſt; beſides,
they neither do deſpiſe the forreign ſubſtance of almoſt all the
Nations of the world; inſomuch that now Strangers come to <hi>Rome</hi> from
all parts of the world, to go to Whores: Therefore you muſt not be offended
with me, nor upbraid me with this, that we muſt level at more ſubſtantial
and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found matters, ſince that the Curtezans of this our City are the
moſt profound and ſubſtantial things perhaps of the whole world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Be it as you pleaſe, I grant you all you can deſire,
becauſe 'tis in my own houſe, where it would not argue good breeding to
enter into diſputes with thoſe<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104221:31"/>that viſit me. I
ſhall only tell you, that this depth and ſubſtance that is in the
Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans, would be worthy our entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if we could find out nothing
more ſubſtantial, nor profound; which by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees goes beyond all
other ſubſtance and depth that ever was known.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I am curious to know what thing you think there is in
<hi>Rome,</hi> that hath a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter depth than Whoredome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>What thing? The Nephew-ſhip, that is a Gulph, an abyſs, a
Sea, a Hell; A Hell that the more damn'd ſpirits it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives into its
embraces, it burns with the greater deſire of having more: A Sea that
ſwallows up of its ſelf the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes procur'd by rapine from Sea-men,
by its proud ſwelling tempeſts. An Abyſs, that admits you not to ſee
thoſe that once throw themſelves into it; it is a Gulf that ſtrikes
terror in all that look upon it. Two lazy Franciſcans with chiopins are
ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently able of themſelves to fill the belly of the greateſt Whore
in the world, and the better if they meet with thoſe that have the Keys of
the Stores at command; theſe grow as fat as Swine with Acorns; but to fill up
this <hi>verago</hi> and deep Abyſs of the Nephew-ſhip, neither Kingdoms,
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104221:32"/>States, People, Seculars, Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, the Earth,
Heaven, Church, nor the whole world are ſufficient. What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon can be
made between the depth of a poor Curtezan, and the gulf of Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? The
depth of ſuch a Lady ſwallows up with ſweetneſs, and the gulf of
Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with bitterneſs: The gulf of a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezan ſeeks nothing but what
is voluntary brought to her; and the <hi>vorago</hi> of Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm obligeth
and conſtrains all perſons to bring Griſt to their Mill. In fine, he that
buries what he hath in the Sea of a Whore; he hath a kind of a prerogative to
return thither to fiſh again; but he that loſeth his ſubſtance in the
Abyſs of the Nephew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, loſeth all hope of ever recovering it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>You will acquaint me with ſo much, that I ſhall grant what
ever you ſay. But how do you underſtand it of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the
Nephewſhip?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The ſubſtance of the Nephewſhip is infinite; ſo that
ſpeaking of this you mention the moſt ſubſtantial thing in the whole
Univerſs; and in effect, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewſhip is nothing but a Quinteſſence
diſtill'd in the Limbeck of the Church, from a great deal of wealth violently
taken<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104221:32"/>both from the one and the other. The ſubſtance of
Curtezans is made up of one ſole ſpecies, they drawing that ſmall wealth
they have either out of the purſe of ſome deſolate Youth, or ſome
inamour'd old Dotard: But the wealth of the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews is of ſuch
ſeveral kinds, that it is impoſſible to know the form of it. For the
Nephews rob day and night, both Men and Women, Citizens and Strangers,
Prieſts and Friars, Married men and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; thoſe that are innocent, and
thoſe that are guilty, ſmall and great; and to conclude, do not ſpare a
whit the Altars themſelves. Nay, I'le go farther, there is ſome of the
Curtezans wealth that helps to make up that of the Nephewſhip; but in that of
the Curtezan, not one farthing of the Nephewſhips ſubſtance. And the
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the Popes Nephews go to Whores without paying any money
for the uſe of their Bodies, whereas the Whores muſt pay the Nephews, that
they may have liberty granted to return the whole for a ſmall matter. See,
this is the kind of ſubſtance that theſe goodly Nephews en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Then you believ'd that I came to diſcourſe with you about
the Nephewſhip, did not you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104221:33"/>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt; and do not you know that the City, Court, nay,
the whole Univerſs, believes it! There is not a Scullion in <hi>Rome,</hi>
that did not imagine when he ſaw us together that we did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer about the
ſtate and condition of the Nephewſhip: And becauſe the very name of the
Nephews (thanks to their unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy actions) is now become odious to Heaven and
Earth, the Gentry and Plebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, therefore is our diſcourſe thought to be
altogether imploy'd in the cenſuring thoſe villainous actions of the moſt
wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nephews; and the evil proceedings of the Nephews of the moſt
ſanctified Popes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>We have diſcourſ'd ſo much of this ſubject, that I think
there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more added.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Dear Brother, you deceive your ſelf; for if the Nephewſhip
goes on <hi>ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitum,</hi> as well in robbing as multiplying conſtantly
the number of their Relations, multiplicity of words will encreaſe
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; and there cannot be found ſo licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious a tongue as will be able
to publiſh the tyrannies that theſe Reigning Nephews exerciſe, not only
againſt the miſerable people of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo againſt the
whole flock of Chriſt; to whoſe prejudice they<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104221:33"/>transform
themſelves into ravening wolves: Nor can there be ſo tenacious a memory, as
to retain thoſe many knaviſh tricks, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions, contempts, torments and
lazineſs, that ſuch a number of Nephews do fill <hi>Rome</hi> withal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>In my judgment we ſhould all be ſilent, now that this evil
is, inevitable. Thoſe miſeries are complain'd of, that can be
redreſſed; but in this caſe where there is no remedy, prudence requires,
we ſhew either our patience in ſuffering thoſe evils, or ſcorn in
deſpiſing them, or a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit humour in diſſembling them. Whilſt
<hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Rome;</hi> that is, as long as <hi>Rome</hi> is under the
Pope, you muſt expect to ſee none but Harpyes in the Church, and
Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeches in the State Eccleſiaſtick: Harpyes to devour and conſume
the ſubſtance of the Subjects; and Horſleeches to ſuck the blood of all
the faithful, even the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bowels that lie moſt conceal'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>But what would you have men leave off talking, when the Nephews
will not leave off doing of miſchief? A fine buſineſs indeed, that the
party offended ſhall be ſooner wearied with ſpeaking, then the offender
with evil doing? That the people of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall make an end of 
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104221:34"/>talking, and yet the Nephews not leave off
aſſaſſinating? That the Nephews have more liberty to rob in
<hi>Rome,</hi> then <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſpeak in the world. The miſerable
ſtate of the Church would grieve to ſee this ſingle tyranny; that is, to
ſee her own mouth ſtopt, and the devouring Bog of the Nephewſhip evermore
open to their damage: Which you have very well bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ'd, by comparing them
to the Horſleech, and calling them Harpyes. But I would have you know, that
that ſo trivial and common Proverb, viz. <hi>like will to like,</hi> is
moſt of all verified in the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, they being by natural inſtinct,
which the <hi>Vatican</hi> communicates unto them (if it be the
<hi>Vatican,</hi> which I am not very certain of; ſince ſome that
eſteem'd themſelves Saints in their own Apartments as ſoon as they went
into the <hi>Vatican</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Devils) Harpyes and Horſleeches, who cannot
converſe with others then Blood-ſuckers and Harpyes, with whom they agree
moſt naturally.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>As for my own part I was ever of this perſwaſion, that there
were no Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyes or Blood-ſuckers, but the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104221:34"/>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Ah Sir, you know the contrary ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, but you will not
relate it: Why, are not the <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> who come moſt of them to
<hi>Rome</hi> laden with Jewiſh Uſury. Horpyes? And the
<hi>Florentines</hi> and <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that forſake <hi>Tuſcany</hi>
to bring their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian Buttocks into the Court of <hi>Rome,;</hi> are not they
Blood-ſuckers? And the <hi>Lucche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that abandon the liberty of
their own Republick, to render themſelves Vaſſals to their Nephewſhips
of <hi>Rome;</hi> are not they both Harpyes and Blood-ſuckers? Now who do
theſe Nephews trade with, but a few of ſuch raſcally Fellows? On whom do
they confer the principal places of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Government, but <hi>Genoeſes,
Seneſes</hi> and <hi>Luccheſes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Really Countrey-man, you are in the right, and I wiſh your
words were ſo prevalent as to penetrate the minds of the Nephews; but in my
opinion it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to hold your peace, now that the Popes Nephews, who
have rendred themſelves the Tyrants of <hi>Rome</hi> for theſe two Ages
hitherto, have ſworn to do all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what the Romans pretend:
And experience makes it ſufficiently manifeſt, becauſe they hear daily
clamours, that they ſhould have regard to the proper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104221:35"/>of the State, to whom, in reaſon, the moſt eminent
Offices and Dignities of the Church did belong. But the tyrannical Nephews
laughing at ſuch lamentations, have not only made it their endeavour to
introduce thouſands of Strangers into the moſt famous places of Judicature,
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the moſt eminent Dignities to them; but have alſo taken
away, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently depriv'd the Citizens of thoſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices which they
enjoy'd for the ſpace of five Ages and better, enriching the
<hi>Lucche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Seneſes</hi> and <hi>Genoeſes</hi> therewith, who, in
effect, are not unlike Harpyes, as you ſay; they having by their extortion
and merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes ſo impoveriſhed this miſerable State, by exporting
the moſt ſtaple Commodities, with an aſſured hope that they ſhall
never return to them again, that it is become the moſt poor, unpeopled and
unhappy of all other States in the World: And will ſtill grow worſe and
worſe; becauſe theſe raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally <hi>Genoeſes, Luccheſes</hi> and
<hi>Seneſes,</hi> have made oath to leave nothing but wooden Gibbets in
<hi>Rome;</hi> to the end, that they may crucifie the Romans both in Body and
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. If other Nations ſhould rob this moſt unfortunate State, there
might one day be ſome reparation expected. But<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104221:35"/>the
<hi>Luccheſes, Seneſes</hi> and <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> when they ſteal from
others, ſwear they will think of any other thing but reſtitution; and
indeed if <hi>Lucca</hi> would reſtore, what her Citizens have taken from
<hi>Rome,</hi> She muſt neceſſarily give the Romans her whole Republick:
The ſame thing muſt the <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> do alſo, or at leaſt pawn
the very ſhirts off of their backs, and being thus naked, enter into a
Nunnery to do penance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Soft a little, how you miſtake? You would ſay in a Convent
of Capuchins, not a Nunnery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I do not erre at all; I ſay they muſt do pennance with Nuns;
and I would have you underſtand, that the <hi>Seneſes,</hi> could not be
more mortified with any thing, then to ſee themſelves depriv'd of
practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with their Ingles, and be conſtrain'd to co-habit with a Sex
ſo much an enemy to their filthy inclinations: Beſides, all the Beards in
<hi>Sueden,</hi> much leſs thoſe of the Capuchins, would not be
ſufficient to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the unbridled luſt of the <hi>Seneſian</hi>
Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites: But this ardent deſire would of it ſelf extinguiſh at the
ſight of that which inflames it; and it is moſt certain, that I would
ſooner truſt one of <hi>Sienna</hi> with a naked Virgin, then a cloath'd
Capuchin:<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104221:36"/>and of this opinion are all the Curtezans of
<hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>You are in the right, Sir. I had forgot it; for I know it as
perfectly as my <hi>A. B. C.</hi> Go on with your diſcourſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> who believe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is an
abuſe introduced among Chriſtians, will never go about to reſtore either
in the whole, or in part, what they have rob'd <hi>Rome</hi> of; becauſe they
had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be taken notice of as rich Jews, then poor Chriſtians; therefore
it is in vain to hope that ever the <hi>Genoeſe</hi> will ſo much as think
of the reſtitution of ſo many Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they have ſtollen from the
State Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick. This in truth is one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt troubles that
hath afflicted my mind; that is, to ſee ſuch a brood of people ſack
<hi>Rome</hi> with greater impiety, then the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of <hi>Charles</hi> the
Fifth did in the time of <hi>Clement</hi> the Seventh, and to carry away the
ſpoils to enrich <hi>Siena, Lucca</hi> and <hi>Genoa;</hi> the
<hi>Geneoſes, Luccheſes</hi> and <hi>Seneſes,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent more
ſtudy and time in raking into the very bowels of the Church to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away
her moſt precious ſubſtance, then ever the <hi>Venetians</hi> did to
enrich <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> with the ſpoils of Infidels. Hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
Jews ſtood in awe of the Romans,<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104221:36"/>expecting every hour that
they would poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes themſelves of <hi>Judea;</hi> and now, the poor Romans
fear three Nations, the <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Luccheſes</hi> and
<hi>Genoeſes,</hi> that are found at <hi>Rome</hi> in ſuch vaſt
multitudes, with no other deſign but to unbowel her,; like Jews under the New
Teſtament, to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own Countrey with the ſpoils ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the
Church, not from Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans only. However, though the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, that
come from this place and that place, rob without any regard to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet
their Larcenies do often remain in the very boſom of <hi>Rome,</hi> whence
the Romans hope to draw ſome comfort.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Great comfort indeed, that poor beggerly hungry dogs, and
thoſe Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers too, that come to gather the Church ſpoils of ſo many
Kingdoms, to reduce the natural Citizens to beggery and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the
whole body of the Roman Nobility, to the Vaſſalages of a few raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
Upſtarts. O how much better had it been for <hi>Constantine</hi> to have left
<hi>Rome</hi> to the Empire, then to give the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> to the
Popes; that muſt afterward deprive themſelves of all to beſtow gifts upon
their Nephews; and which is worſe, ſuch Nephews as are fitter far to
ſerve as<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104221:37"/>Sextons to the Temple, then to command the Church
as Princes! If the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews were capable of governing the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire with
honour, we might bear with it; but the Devil himſelf would burſt with rage
to ſee the Paraſites themſelves fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the greateſt abſurdities
imaginable: The Romans only complain, and yet the Church hath its ſhare; but
in thoſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did actions, quite void of reaſon and judgment, which they
commit, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to command Princes, not the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans only, and the
Church extreamly ſuffers thereby, but farther, the Princes of the world being
prejudiced thereby, are greatly obliged in point of policy to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
themſelves; I will not ſay with the Church or Pope, but his Nephews, that
ſell and give, <hi>ad libitum,</hi> the Church, the Pope, the People,
Kingdoms, Offices and Dignities, having all ſworn never to devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from the
natural inſtinct of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewſhip; which is to manage every thing in
deſpite of Church and Princes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you I am not come hither to treat of ſuch vulgar and
common things; about which even in the very Coblers ſtalls there are night
and day long diſcourſes, that choak up the air it ſelf, inſomuch that 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104221:37"/>they leave a greater ſtench in thoſe places, then the
filth that is in the old Shoes they mend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>You underſtand it, and I you, let us then diſcourſe of
things that more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly concern you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>And what things are thoſe that concern you moſt, and are
more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar at preſent?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The death of the Pope, is not that a ſubject worthy to be
celebrated by us with joy and triumph, and for us to make large reflections
upon? O God! and what greater happineſs could ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to our City, as
alſo to the ſtate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick, nay, the whole world, then to ſee
her ſelf freed from thoſe chains, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe hath been ſhackled for
the ſpace of eleven years? All the people did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at the entrance of
<hi>Alexander</hi> the Great into the City, becauſe he entred to give freedom
to the Citizens, peace to the People, plenty of food and honour to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies:
But when they ſaw him afterwards dead, they gave themſelves over to grief,
and ſhed rivers of tears, being aſſur'd they ſhould loſe that in his
death, which they gain'd in his life. On the contrary, we poor Romans,
becauſe that <hi>Alexander</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104221:38"/>gave us, during his whole
life, ſufficient cauſe of weeping, taking no other thought in the whole
courſe of his Pontificature, but to afflict the Citizens, lay heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
on the People, impoveriſh Families, and to bring ſcarcity in the State: For
this reaſon we are oblig'd to rejoyce in his death, that gave us ſuch
cauſe of ſorrow in his life. Even now we may believe the people of
<hi>Rome</hi> to be belov'd of God, now that he hath deliver'd her from the
ſlavery of this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of the Chriſtians: And if the Jews had
their Chains taken off in the month of <hi>May;</hi> the Chains alſo of the
<hi>Chigi</hi> ought to be broken off of the hands of Chriſtians even at the
ſame time, it may be on the ſame day, that the world may ſee the
Chriſtians are no leſs protected by Chriſt in the New, then the Jews by
God in the Old Teſtament; with this only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that they paſſed
through the red Sea dry footed, before they came into the Land of Promiſe;
but the Chriſtians, and above all the Romans, are conſtrain'd to paſs
through an Ocean of tears, not dry footed, becauſe that the cauſe of
weeping is not remov'd by the death of <hi>Alexander;</hi> he having left us
ſo many Gabels, that it is probable they may never be taken off, and 
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104221:38"/>by conſequence we ſhall be ever oblig'd to ſhed
tears: So that the Jews may be call'd a more happy people being come out of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> then we out of the priſon of the <hi>Seneſes;</hi>
becauſe we have not our entire freedom, whereas the Jews enjoy'd an
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute liberty; yet in truth we ought to rejoyce much more to ſee
<hi>Alexander</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the midſt of our Ocean of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then the
Jews heretofore to ſee <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> overwhelmed in the Red Sea: For to
be plain with you, <hi>Alexander</hi> did handle the Chriſtians far worſe
then <hi>Pharoah</hi> did the Jews of old. But what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Don
Mario,</hi> that modern <hi>Silla</hi> of the Romans? His cruelties are
infinite; and though the Devil hath given him leave to ſurvive his Brother,
no matter for that, we muſt not therefore ceaſe our rejoycing; it being a
kind of petty death to him, and life to us, that he is put out of the
<hi>Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> and his government of the Town. Nevertheleſs, it was but
agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that as <hi>Alexander</hi> left his Brother, and all
the raſcally Chigians for more months in <hi>Sienna,</hi> whence he leapt
into the Popedom, only richly to prepare the <hi>Vatican</hi> for their nobler
reception, that he ſhould now again deſcend into hell before 
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104221:39"/>any of the <hi>Chigi</hi>'s, to prepare Palaces and
Apartments, to the end that he might receive thoſe his Brothers and Nephews,
according to their merits; and all of them indeed deſerve nothing elſe, but
to go to the manſion of Antichriſt, ſince that they have been more
impious then Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts in <hi>Christendom.</hi> We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hope,
that we ſhall ſee this City free from that plague, before many months are
paſt, as we have alſo ſeen the <hi>Vatican</hi> rid of thoſe Tyrants.
Truly we are oblig'd to <hi>Alexander</hi> for going to the other world, but we
had been far more ingag'd to him, had he taken his journey ten years ago;
becauſe then all perſons would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, as an article of their
Faith, that he had gone to Heaven; whereas now there are ſome Chriſtians in
<hi>Rome,</hi> that make it a ſcruple of Conſcience to believe, that he is
not gone to Hell. Furthermore, the obligation had been doubled, if he had
pleaſ'd to conduct with him, if not the whole Houſe of the
<hi>Chigi</hi>'s, yet at leaſt that moſt excellent Brother of his, who is
the Head of the <hi>Chigi</hi>'s, Neck of the <hi>Bichi</hi>'s, Body of the
<hi>Ciaii,</hi> Feet of <hi>Siena,</hi> and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally a member of the Devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104221:39"/>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Don't you be offended, Dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that <hi>Don Mario</hi>
had not the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fretation over the Stygian Lake at the ſame time with his
moſt holy Brother; becauſe the Devil, who knew the crimes both of the one
and the other, would not hazard <hi>Charon</hi>'s Bark through the
tempeſtuous waves of the Stygian water, fearing leaſt he ſhould ſink
himſelf by the way, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great weight of the ſins of theſe
two Brethren, and ſo Hell ſhould happen to loſe two ſuch happy Victims.
There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt believe that <hi>Lucifers</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was, that
<hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould be firſt conducted thither, and then <hi>Don
Mario</hi> ſhould be ſnatched away, becauſe it will be requiſit to
build a new Boat on purpoſe to waft over ſo large a body, laden with ſo
many rapines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>You think not amiſs; but for my own particular, I do now
imagine with my ſelf, that this is one of the intrigues of
<hi>Alexanders</hi> policy, deſiring to make himſelf known to be a great
Polititian at the end of his Papacy, as he did ſeem to be at the beginning;
when he underſtood ſo well how to deceive the World and the Church,
<hi>Chriſtendom</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> feigning himſelf averſs to the
promotion of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104221:40"/>ſo that every one believ'd
him to be pious, and diſintereſſed with his blood; and at his end he did
pretend he would have this alſo to be underſtood in the other world, to
encreaſe his glory, if he had gone to heaven, according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, or
abate his torment, when ever the misfortune ſhould befall him to go to hell,
which he did not believe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>On the contrary, if he had been an able Politician, he had taken
<hi>Don Mario</hi> along with him, becauſe the Devils would have yielded in
all things, and all manner of wayes to the train of his Infernal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
and ſo had let the poor Pope go ſhift for himſelf in Purgatory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The Devils would not have been ſo fooliſh to loſe ſuch a
prey, which they have for ſo long a time been in chaſe of. I would have you
underſtand, that the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Alexander</hi> (if ſo be that he is
damn'd, as we ought religiouſly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) had no other riſe, but the
force of diabolick temptations; for whilſt he liv'd without delivering up
himſelf into the hands of thoſe that uſe to tempt the Popes, he wrought
none but wonders, miracles, and holy works; but the Devil no ſooner began to
poſſeſs himſelf of his heart, but<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104221:40"/>he became a
<hi>Judas</hi> to the Church, an <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariot</hi> to the People, a
<hi>Jew</hi> to the Romans, and a <hi>Pilat</hi> to all
<hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But how can the Devils enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of the Pope, if it
be the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Are you alſo one of the Diſciples to thoſe falſe
Divines, that beſtow the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt upon the Pope by weight and meaſure.
Thoſe Tales that the Pope is guided by the holy Ghoſt, are Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
inventions to blind the eyes of the faithful, to the end that they ſhould not
be offended with the actions of ſuch Popes that are Wolves and not Shepherds,
that fleece the Flock of Chriſt, but do not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it; that hold the knife
in their hand like Butchers, and not the paſtoral rod like Paſtors; and in
truth there are none but a few beggarly Whores; ſome mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant
Fellow-friars; and peradventure ſome kind of novice of the Capuchins order,
that believe the Popes directed by the holy Ghoſt: As for the reſt, men of
ſolid judgment ſmile at all the Theologians write, and give them the
liberty to ſay what they pleaſe, whilſt they believe what they ſee;
that is, ſo long as they find in the Pope's a holy way of operation they
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104221:41"/>them holy; but when afterwards they diſcover
deeds of darkneſs in them, they judge them Devils. One of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
impieties in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> is the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which puniſheth
moſt tyrannically thoſe poor faithful ones, that mov'd with a ſcruple of
conſcience, maintain pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, either by the hand or tongue, that theſe
Popes are ſubject to erre, whom they in truth ſee full of error. God
himſelf by the mouth of his Prophet inſtructs us, that, <hi>Cum ſancto
ſanctus eris, cum perverſo perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">"With the holy thou ſhalt be holy, and with
the wicked thou ſhalt be wicked."</q> Yet by all means the moſt reverend
devils of the Inquiſition, will have an abſolute power, that the faithful
ſhall be holy with the wicked, though in deſpight of them they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
therefore we will not ſay they do worſe, becauſe this ſtopping of the
mouth in publick places by menaces, doth ſo ſwell the hearts of the moſt
ſenſible Chriſtians that they endure with great violence the more zealous
pens of thoſe <hi>Nicodemuſſes</hi> that for fear are forc't to abſcond
themſelves in their moſt privat Studies, making their Writings fly to the
utmoſt parts of the Earth, where the men are not ſo credu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lous 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104221:41"/>as to believe white to be black, and black white. In my
opinion it ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Inquiſitors, that the faithful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
the Pope's infallible whilſt they do not errr, and are guided by the holy
Ghoſt; whilſt they work according to the gifts of the holy Spirit, and
conformably to the laws wherewith that bleſſed Spirit hath furniſhed the
Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I would fain know, at what time, you believe that the Devil took
poſſeſſion of the heart of Pope <hi>Alexander?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you forthwith; but firſt I would give you to
underſtand, that the Pope's cannot pretend to be the true Vicars of Chriſt,
becauſe they are elected by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cardinals, that are all of the devil;
from whom, as being an enemy to the Church, they cannot expect any thing but
wicked inſpiration; and withal, if the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be granted to be good, the
Pope that is inaugurated, ought to be acknowledged as a moſt holy and
infallible perſon by the faithful, until that he delivers himſelf up to
theſe devils, who oblige him to ſin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>And this farther I deſire to be ſatisfied in, having
ſpoken to you concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Alexander</hi> in particular, to underſtand
ſomewhat of the other Pope's in general,<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104221:42"/>now that the
calamities of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, to ſee that which is univerſal
made particular.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The Devils that tempt the Popes to ſin, are their Nephews,
Dear Brother, theſe make him deviate from the right path, and lead him
through mountains and ſteep places: Theſe blind his eyes, and make him walk
in the dark. Theſe are they that tye up his hands, ſo that he can do
nothing for others, becauſe he doth all things for them. Theſe ſtop his
ears, that he cannot hear the cryes of the people. Theſe drive all good
thoughts out of his mind, to fill it with thoſe that are bad and wicked. In
ſum, the Nephews are thoſe that engage the Popes in ſin; whence it is,
that after they are laden with ſins, they go to give an account at the divine
Tribunal, for that liberty that they give to the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>To this purpoſe I remember, that a certain Prelat related a
certain dream of his to one of his Confidents in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and I think it
is now about three daies ago. The dream was, that he ſeem'd to ſee a Pope
kneeling at the Foot-ſtool of the Almighty God, who being examin'd by him why
he had govern'd the Church<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104221:42"/>ſo ill, afflicted the People,
and ſpoiled his Altars. The good Pope all bedewed with tears, anſwer'd with
<hi>Adam. Thoſe Nephews</hi> (not that woman which ſerved as an excuſe to
<hi>Adam</hi>) <hi>which thou hast given me, O Lord, have forced me to
ſin.</hi> At which words the Prelat ſaid, that the Almighty made this
reply. <hi>Thou lyeſt, for it was not I that gave thee theſe Nephews, but
thou thy ſelf haſt introduc'd them into the</hi> Vatican <hi>of thy own
accord.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>I alſo heard another dream told a Prieſt, yet relating
particularly to the Popes; that thought he ſaw a Pope in Hell diſputing
with his Nephews; they belſhing out againſt one another the groſſeſt
curſes and lyes in the world; the poor Pope re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the Nephews for
their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Nephews the Uncle for his facility. The
miſerable Uncle ſaid. <hi>Ah you, cruel and wicked perſons! Ah you
Thieves and Devils! You are the perſons that were the occaſion of my being
here: I have gain'd darkneſs and obſcurity, to leave you the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
of gold and ſilver; I have cauſ'd my ſelf to be impriſon'd in hell, for
that liberty which I allowed you in the</hi> Vatican. <hi>I have choſen for
my ſelf the pains of this Abyſs, for beſtowing too much honour on you
in</hi> Rome.<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104221:43"/>
                  <hi>Therefore, O ye Nephews! he accurſed,
and let thoſe heaps of gold, ſilver and riches, that I permitted you to
diſappropriate from the Church, and ſteal from the People, be turn'd into
everlaſting flames, and ſerpents that may ever war againſt you.</hi> On
the other hand the Nephews repli'd. <hi>Be you accurſ'd we will not ſay,
Uncle, but Enemy; you that have thrown your ſelf into our arms, to caſt us
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the embraces of the Devil; you that have beſtow'd ſo much gold upon
us, that it is of no uſe, but to purchaſe Hel-flames withal; you that have
made us great in the world, to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated in Hell: Be you therefore
accurſ'd, that was the cauſe of our damnation, and not we of yours, as you
affirm; for we did not call you from the</hi> Vatican, <hi>where you were, to
come and dwell with us; but you invited us from our own habitation, where we
did reſide, to give us poſſeſſion of the</hi> Vatican. Theſe are
but dreams, yet experience hath ſhewn us many things of the like nature that
are true; and really we have ſeen too many holy Popes before they ſuffered
the Nephews to ſway, who after their admiſſion, became abſolute Devils.
Good God! that the Nephews ſhould corrupt the Uncle, and the Uncle the
Nephews, it being a real truth, that the one ſerves to tempt the 
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104221:43"/>other. But now to return to <hi>Alexander,</hi> I will tell
thee, that the Devil that entred into his heart was <hi>Don Mario;</hi> he
having tempted him to commit all the deviliſh tricks that he was guilty
of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>If you ſhould enter too deeply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hell of the
Nephewſhips and Popes, we ſhould never get out again; I am not come hither
to ſee the Devils Lodgings, but your own ſelf, and therefore I entreat you
to alter your diſcourſe, we having ſufficiently expatiated on that
ſubject which battens you; all the world knows, that as Swine grow fat with
eating Acorns, and wallowing in the moſt filthy mire, ſo you nouriſh your
ſelf by turning and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your diſcourſe concerning the Nephews, and I
really believe that their dirty actions have a more ſtinking ſavour, then
the very filth that fattens Swine; Sir Reverence to the Company, and his
Excellency <hi>Don Mario.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>You deceive your Neighbour and Enemy by this kind of talk, and I
plainly ſee that you will be overcome on all ſides: Now then let us ſpeak
of that which is ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to your humour, ſuite that you will not
condeſcend to ſpeak of that which agrees with mine. Let us end theſe
argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104221:44"/>concerning the <hi>Seneſes</hi> with this
fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy talk, who value a Civet-box much more then they do a bottle of ſweet
waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water. Let us proceed to the Ladies urine, becauſe that will
pleaſe your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; wherefore it behooves you to know that our diſcourſe
at the beginning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Nephews was not amiſs, ſince that all
proceedings ariſe from them, they holding as it were the keys of the
Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, rather of Sodomie, you would ſay, if I miſtake not; for
they will not enter any but certain ſtraight gates, which are more ſuitable
to the Palace of the <hi>Vatican;</hi> and that is the reaſon ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Ganimeds</hi> are found at Court, and ſo few Nephews in the
Bawdy-houſe; The Lordly Nephews fancying thoſe viands that are exchanged
for Eccleſiaſtical Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, not ſuch drinks as are purchaſ'd with
the expence of ready money. The Popes Nephews are not ſuch
<hi>Mammalucks,</hi> to ſpend their money in going to a Whore, with the
danger of loſing that neutrality which they ought to maintain with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
Crowns, ſhewing themſelves too much intereſſed with the French party;
it being now adays a common thing in <hi>Rome,</hi> that<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104221:44"/>he
that exerciſeth himſelf with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Curtezans, though he be a Spaniard
by birth, and an Italian by practice; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, he becomes a
French man both in blood and conſtitution, in a ſmall time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>That policy of neutrality the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews ſufficiently obſerve;
becauſe they impoſe Taxes upon the Whores, forcing them to pay even for the
very confeſſion of their own ſins; and with the filthy gain they draw
from thence, they make Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of Ingles; and that which is more to be
admir'd is, that they give the people to underſtand this is done out of a
meer act of charity; as if it were a pious thing to leave the high way of
Chriſtianity, and follow the Spherrical way of the Turk. ſome perſons
believe, that is, ſuch as are more curious in the obſervation of the
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of things, that this cuſtom was brought into <hi>Rome,</hi>
together with the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewſhip,; yet however, 'tis reported, that it never had
ſuch a vogue before, as it had when the <hi>Seneſes</hi> had the command of
the <hi>Vatican;</hi> which is the reaſon that now the poor Whores are weary
of their very lives, to ſee the bread taken out of their mouths, and have a
cuſtom introduc'd, to<pb n="82" facs="tcp:104221:45"/>eat no other bread but what is made
of corn grinded in a Wind-mill, ſlighting the flower that is made in a
Water-mill as an inconſiderable thing; they are reſolv'd with themſelves
to make uſe of the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whilſt the Chair is vacant, to promote
their own advantage, and endeavour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a cuſtom of chooſing a
Pope after their own mode, and to their own fancy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I have now underſtood many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in this buſineſs;
which tend to no other end but to ſtir up a deſire in me of knowing every
the ſmalleſt punctilio; ſo that you by acquainting me with what you know,
and I you with what I apprehend, we ſhall mutually ſatisfie one another; by
our arguing, for the future upon thoſe matters which deſerve moſt to be
publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as we think convenient.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>The ſubject in truth is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to raiſe an argument;
it being a novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and never heretofore heard of, that the Whores do pretend
to have a ſhare in the Election of the Pope; and that which increaſeth the
wonder is, that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes are not ſo vain and airy, as they ſeem
to be, for they appear to me as grounded upon the ſolid baſis of
reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>O, I can by no means entertain<pb n="83" facs="tcp:104221:45"/>this in my
thoughts; I ever took all that to be a kind of Curtezan-like liberty, and a
thing rather ridiculous then ſubſtantial: And indeed to ſpeak rationally
what (a Devil) have the Curtezans to do with the Election of the Pope?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>And to anſwer you in reaſon, what (a Devil) hath the Pope to
do to draw ſo much money from the Whores, for the maintainance of his Nephews
pride? To oblige the Whores to give great ſtore of contribution-money, to
force them to pay ſo many Gabels and Taxes; this is nothing elſe but a
permiſſion for them to ſin after their own mode; to ſell their own
fleſh at cheaper rates, then that which is vended at the Shambles, and to
leave no ſtone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, to make even thoſe great ravenous birds of prey;
the Friars to be taken by the lime-twigs, and when they are once catch't, they
leave all their feathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, and ſome of them break their necks by
ſtruggling to get their liberty. Now this Theologian will ſay, that is no
leſs ſin to grant the Whores the power of chooſing the Pope, then the
Pope liberty to oblige the Whores to play the Whores, to pay off thoſe Taxes
which the Nephews impoſe upon their way of Livelyhood?<pb n="84" facs="tcp:104221:46"/>The
reaſon which mov'd the Whores to ſuch pretences are many. Firſt, the
Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans ſay, why ſhall not we chooſe that Pope, that muſt be
maintain'd by us? Why ſhould not we pay money to one that is elected to
pleaſe anothers humour? Why ſhould others ſet up a Pope, and we empty our
own purſes to fill his coffers? We do not refuſe the payment of thoſe
contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions that are laid upon us, but very well may we deny him to be our
Pope, who is not ours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>If they are furniſhed with no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſons then theſe,
they will never bring their pretended deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of having power to elect a Pope, to a period.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are in a manner inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, they have a far
greater number; but the buſineſs is this, in <hi>Rome</hi> it is not
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but the intereſts of thoſe that are the moſt powerful, that
prevail in the Popes Election. Wherefore if it were granted, that the Whores
ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Conclave, and have a free vote as well as the
Cardinals, in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pope, they would do no good, becauſe the
Ingles, who are more eſteem'd, would procure all the votes in favour of them,
and ſo would ſet up a Pope accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<pb n="85" facs="tcp:104221:46"/>to their own
fancy, in deſpight of all the Whores, not in <hi>Rome</hi> only, but the
whole world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Don't you know that the ſin of Sodomie makes not ſuch an
noiſe in the world as that of Wenching? which is the reaſon that the moſt
conſelentious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, and thoſe Cardinals, that are the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
pretenders to the Papacy, turn away their face when they ſpy a pretty little
poor Whore go to Maſs, or a moſt excellent Curtezan to ride for her
recreation in ſome Ambaſſadours Coach, as if they ſaw the devil with
his horns, croſſing themſelves often times with the left hand, and yet
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards take a pride in ſpending whole dayes, and the greater part of the
night in their Chamber, with ſome little Sodomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Boy or filthy Ingle:
And what is the reaſon? Becauſe that as ſoon as the Whores of
<hi>Rome</hi> do but once touch the Pontificial Glove of any Prelat, they grow
ſo proud, that the Roman Lords can ſcarce have the honour to touch their
Toe; and ſo much the worſe if it be a Cardinal; then they go about to every
Bawdy-houſe proudly mounted on their Chioapins; boaſting that they ſerv'd
as a Mare to his moſt illuſtrious Lordſhip, and as an Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:104221:47"/>to his Eminencie: For in truth it is the nature of a Whore
to diſcover all ſhe does; and the Boy's to keep ſecret what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done
to him; therefore, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats and Cardinals to preſerve the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of
the Purple and Epiſcopal Robe, think it well done to ſlight the Ladies,
that they may avoid all occaſion of ſcandal to Chriſtians, and ſpend
their time with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitical Boy's, with whoſe friendſhip being a long time
acquainted, ſerves for a uſe of edification to the Court; now the major
part of the Courtiers lick their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ends, and take no notice of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>If they would be content, the one with the Bull-calf, the other
with the Cow, the thing would be more tolerable; but in <hi>Rome</hi> they
ſteer another courſe; whilſt they that diet themſelves with the
ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry food of the Bull-calf, do not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refrain from taking ſome
ſmall mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Cow, which ſerves as ſauce the better to
ſharpen the appetite to have their belly full of bulling; and they who feed
ordinarily on the Cows fleſh, will for all that, like women, with child,
ſometimes ſatisfie their longing, that the <hi>Infant</hi> in the womb may
have no mark of the <hi>Bull-calf.</hi> 'Tis true, that theſe devout
Arſeworms, do<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104221:47"/>like him, that ſaid the Liver was not
fleſh; wherefore he did eat fleſh on the <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> liver on the
<hi>Friday,</hi> without any ſcruple of conſcience. The Hereticks ſpend
the leiſure time of the day in murmuring at the Courts proceedings in this
buſineſs; and there are thouſands who have been juſt upon the point of
forſaking hereſie, and becoming good Catholicks, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards were
diverted from thoſe holy thoughts, by ſeeing Bull-beef ſold, as it were
in a market among the Roman Prelats; and in truth that kind of victuals is had
in ſo high eſteem at <hi>Rome,</hi> that even the greateſt Courtiers call
it, <hi>the Cardinals bit;</hi> which is no other then a helliſh kind of food
that deſerves to be burn't in the fire, and reduc'd to aſhes, that ſo by
this means it may be abſolutely forgotten. Nature hath diſtributed things
according to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral order, ſo that the deſtroying that order is no other
then to bid a Turd in Natures teeth, and conſequently to transform ones
ſelf into an animate beaſt. In ſum, the ſin of Sodomie is a contagious
vice that hath infected the Roman Court; inſomuch that all
<hi>Chriſtendom</hi> reſents it, becauſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Superiours are
imitated by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors; and it is a common maxim, the head<pb n="88" facs="tcp:104221:48"/>being once corrupted, all the members are likewiſe. To redreſs
theſe diſorders, it is neceſſary we ſhould introduce the Cuſtom of
permitting Curtezans to make choiſe of the Pope; becauſe if they ſhould
once get a Pope of their own ſide, they would methodically lay down thoſe
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary rules that are for the good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of humane frailty, and
all thoſe Pages, and little Pages, Abbats, and little Abbats, Lords, and
little Lords, whoſe will is their law; Prelats, and little Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats,
Cardinals, and little Cardinals, Popes, and little Popes, would be baniſhed
the Court: It being a thing confirm'd by long experience, that they which bear
the Baſs in the Chamber, can alſo carry the Treble in Councils,
Congregations and Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The golden age would be again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd in
<hi>Rome,</hi> if the gold could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd out of the hands of thoſe
Youths that profane it, and left to the diſpoſal of thoſe good Curtezans,
who ſupply the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Apoſtolick Chamber, and who
voluntarily contribute to the management of the Chriſtian war againſt the
Turk. Who will not ſay, that it is more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to give the Papacy to
theſe Ladies that give to the Pope, rather than to thoſe<pb n="89" facs="tcp:104221:48"/>Ingles that ſpoil both Pope and Popedom. Two things make me deſire
to ſee the Cuſtom of chooſing a Pope by the Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans in their Conclave
introduced. Firſt, to take away that filthy ſtench out of the noſtrils of
thoſe ſtrangers that go to <hi>Rome,</hi> and cannot endure to ſee ſo
many Ingles in the habit of Clergy-men, with their Cod-piece points untied in
every corner of the City, and ſuch a number of Clergy-men that ſmell ſo
rankly of Sodomie. The ſecond is, that we may not ſee ſo much ordure made
into Comfits, with moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſweat of the moſt eminent offices of
the Church: Since that the now moſt ſacred Dignities inſtituted to
ſerve for ornament, to the Eccleſiaſtical Order, ſerve for Sugar to
make Confections withal: Now that I have ſaid it once, there needs no further
repetition. All theſe things will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſ'd, if the Curtezans can but
at any time get the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Vatican:</hi> Theſe,
theſe are they that muſt redreſs this evil; that is, become natural to
the Court, ſcandalous to Hereticks, dreadful to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and terrible to
the whole world. Theſe, theſe muſt neceſſarily regain the Prelats
their reputation, the Cardinals their liberty, the <hi>Vatican</hi> its honour,
and<pb n="90" facs="tcp:104221:49"/>the City her ornament: Theſe, theſe are the
perſons that will remove that ſcandal that is all up and down the world; by
chaſing away all thoſe Commanders from the Court that are too haughty in
their government, the reward of their obedience to the Nephewſhip with too
low a genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection: Theſe, theſe are they that will root out of the earth
that common belief that is generally held of <hi>Rome,</hi> and will make it
appear that the Pope keeps his Chair in a Chriſtian <hi>Rome,</hi> and not a
Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I am alſo ſometimes yet of that perſwaſion, having made
no mean reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on a matter of ſo great importance; but ſince that,
perſons of mature judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have put me out of theſe thoughts; for to
acquaint you with things as they are, or at leaſt as they ought to be, if at
any time our little Whores and Wenches ſhould gain the command of the
<hi>Vatican,</hi> they would play the Devil, nay, do worſe, with their fond
impertient diſcourſes, their Loves and Lovers, and would ſtudy a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
ſubtilties and ſtratagems to entertain the Court ſometimes in one
Houſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in another, at Faſts, Recreations, and with Muſick,
and keeping an open<pb n="91" facs="tcp:104221:49"/>Houſe, would treat them with all
ſorts of viands, whether boil'd or roſted; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, being perſons
naturally minding their own Intereſts, they would even deprive the Pope of
his Robes, and the Cardinals of their Purple, to furniſh their own Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
with Tapeſtry; to the end, that that reddiſh colour might incite him the
more to ſuffer the martyrdom of turning his back, who loves not to ſee the
face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Would to God that it would once come to paſs that the Pope
ſhould have his Robes token off his ſhoulders, and the Cardinals the Purple
off their backs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then the people would in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure find a
way to be comforted, ſeeing thoſe Governours that deſcribe them,
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed by others; for the Curtezans will never be able by their
careſſing the Pope, to deprive him of the thouſandth part of what he by
violence robs the people. To believe that the Concubines, can, by their joynt
intereſts, bring more damage to the publick Treaſury, then thoſe
thouſands of Boys do, that ſuck the blood of the <hi>Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> is but
an erroneous faith; becauſe there is no compariſon to be made between the
damage that is done to the Court by the Ladies, who for the moſt part have 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:104221:50"/>their eyes looking up towards Heaven, and thoſe ſilly
Boys, who, like the ſeed of the Devil, incline themſelves alwayes to kiſs
the Earth; the confideration of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them is ſufficient to prove
this; the number of the Sodomitical Boys in the Court exceeding infinitly that
of the Whores, whence we may eaſily gather that larger expences are
requiſit to the maintaining a greater, then a ſmaller num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But if we
pry into the buſineſs more narrowly, the reaſon will be found on the
Curtezans ſide. Firſt, a few yards of ſlight ſilk, cloth of Gold or
Silver, will ſerve to accoutre theſe Ladies; but to cover the nakedneſs
of the bare Buttocks of ſo many Ingles, there muſt be ſomewhat elſe
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a few yards of Cloth of Gold or Silk; there is a neceſſity to
take away A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacies from the Dacary, Offices from the Court, and Curatſhips
from the City, to cloath ſuch a crew of raſcally follows; and yet theſe
curſed Citizens of the Sodomiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Brothel Houſe are not ſatisfied with
ready money and cloaths, but will have annual Revenues, and Benefices to them
and their Heirs for ever; they judging their profeſſion to be as to the
eſtimate invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and by this means thoſe Prelats that 
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:104221:50"/>have planted a thouſand good works in Heaven come to be
depriv'd of their offices and Dignites, to inveſt theſe bare-breech't dogs
with them, who never did any thing in their lives, but plant Coleworts in Earth
that was never dig'd up. O how much better would it be to leave the Papacy to
the diſcretion of theſe Ladies that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with little, than to the
licentiouſneſs of thoſe Younglings that graſp at all. Come what will of
it, we ſhould never be ſenſible of ſo many cryes of the People, tears
of the Prelats, and ſuch univerſal ſcandals. The Hereticks, who puniſh
with burning that nefandous wickedneſs that is ſo ſweet in <hi>Rome,</hi>
and the luſtful and carnal copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with women, with the whip,
impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and ſometimes with the loſs of life: If they were to make
choice of a Pope, I am confident they would ſooner elect a Stranger than a
Sodomite; and I believe there is none but the Devil, that would rather have a
Sodomit than a Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger. However I will believe the Popes to be chaſt,
their reins tyed up, and free from all carnal pollution; but what doth all this
ſignifie, if they ſuffer Brothel-Houſes to be in the Court, that for the
moſt part go mask't under the names of Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries?<pb n="94" facs="tcp:104221:51"/>How
can the Hereticks, nay, the very Catholicks themſelves, imagine that Pope
chaſt, that receives great ſums from Bawdy-houſe Contributions? How can
they think him to be innocent, if he hath ſuch daily commerce with ſin? How
is it poſſible he ſhould be worſhipped as a Saint, if he permits all
manner of vices to be uncheck't and unpuniſhed throughout the City, worſe
then the Devil himſelf would do? How can he be able to free himſelf from
thoſe accuſations that he is taxed with by the faithful, <hi>viz.</hi> that
he keeps off the deſerving, and calls thoſe that are moſt ignorant to the
Court, that he exhauſteth the puplick Treaſury of the Church, and
diſpoſeth of Eccleſiaſtical Dignities to private perſons; when the
proofs are daily apparent? There are no other perſons found going up and down
the ſtairs of the <hi>Vatican,</hi> but old Sodomitical Boys, ſome of them
go to receive the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their Sodomitical Sacrifice offered to the Devil
for many years; and others coming thither laden with gratuities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd for
their great ſervices done to thoſe that take a pride to have their
ſtanding-chamber in the Arſehole of <hi>Rome.</hi> What infamous cuſtom
reigns there now in <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:104221:51"/>which hath the paternal
benediction of his Holineſs? This little Lord, becauſe he hath carried an
Abbot on his back, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that an Abbacie of right belongs to him, and he
obtains it: The other reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Chamber-fellow no ſooner deſires a
Biſhoprick, but it is granted, becauſe he was Mule to a Prelat; and many of
them think they deſerve a Cardinals Cap, which they obtain before they demand
it; becauſe the acts of humility in thoſe young men in the preſence of
the Cardinals, is in <hi>Rome</hi> rewarded with the Purple: as if the
Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Hat were made to cover their heads that bow down to the very ground;
to the end that the bowing down of the head ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving raiſ'd the back parts,
the head ought alſo to be raiſ'd for the bowing of the back-parts. The Pope
is the cauſe of all this, becauſe he does not, or ſeems not to take
notice of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>You run impertinently from one thing to another, Dear Brother:
What need we talk of the Pope if he be dead! We are met here to diſcourſe
of the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the new Pope; therefore there is no neceſſity for us to
give our judgement of the faults of the dead, nor of thoſe that ſhall live,
which we know not out of what<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104221:52"/>place they will come, I had
almoſt ſaid are born.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks you ſeem to betray your ſimplicity. The Pope never
dyes, he lives alwaies in ſpight of the Devil, though he ſhould deſtroy
one every day. The men only dye that carry a reſemblance of the Pope, and
that have the Popedom at their diſpoſal during life; leaving every thing to
his ſucceſſion when he dies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>If it be ſo, then we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay all that was ſpoken a
little before, that many Popes are damned by their Nephews. How can this be,
that they can live al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, and yet go to Hell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>If you could not underſtand me, I cannot help that, if you did
not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend my meaning, that was no fault of mine. I do not mean that the
Popes are damn'd; on the contrary, I believe this as an undoubted article of my
Faith, that whilſt they are Popes, they can by no means go to Hell; becauſe
the Popedom makes the Popes Popes, and that is a thing that is alwaies left as
an Inheritance to the Church, a torment to <hi>Rome,</hi> an affliction to the
People, and for the mortification of the Hereticks. Yet thoſe perſons who
have had the Papacy, which hath been alwaies<pb n="97" facs="tcp:104221:52"/>ſuppoſed by
certain perſons, may be damn'd, and do damn themſelves. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; A
Porter carrying a Bale of Silk, falls down dead under his burthen; yet this
doth not make the propriety of him to whom it belongs to dye alſo with him;
but there is ſoon found ſome other perſon who takes it up and carries it
to the Owner; and although the Porter ſhould go to the Devil, the Bale of
Silk would not be alſo condemn'd to go thither. Now thoſe that have been
Popes, and govern'd amiſs, are damn'd; but the Papacy is not, <hi>verbi
gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:</hi> I believe <hi>Alexander</hi> the Seventh, who was a Pope (I bring
this in only as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) is gone to Hell, not the Papacy that was govern'd
by him: And therefore the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans that underſtand the nature &amp; the
uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of thoſe perſons that are call'd to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy better then
others, can diſtinguiſh, as to their humane actions, thoſe Popes that are
ſav'd, and thoſe that are damn'd; for the Tree is known by his fruit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>This is a doctrine in the Goſpel, <hi>Ex fructibus eorum
cognoſcetis eos,</hi> You ſhall know them by their fruit: But the Popes are
exempted from all this, becauſe they are not ſubject to the Rules contained
in the Goſpel; they having a faculty which Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians<pb n="98" facs="tcp:104221:53"/>have given them, to create Goſpels according to their own humour,
and to frame Rules to their own fancy, jeſting at the ſupream authority
that is found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; it being enough for them to cauſe that to be written
which agrees better with their own temper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>That which you ſay is certainly true; but yet they know very
well, they have not ſo great authority as is allowed them; and you have a
teſtimony of it in <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, who diſcourſing one day with
one of his intimate and very familiar Theologians, concerning the doctrine of
<hi>Luther,</hi> contrary to the power of the Pope, and the Divine informing
him, that <hi>Luther</hi> among thoſe opinions that he diſperſed abroad,
one was, that he did every where deny, and inſtruct every one, that it was
not true, that the Pope had the Keys both of Heaven and Hell in his
poſſeſſion. Good <hi>Leo,</hi> making a jeaſt of it, anſwered the
Divine: <hi>No matter for that, let him prate what he will, he ſhall not
deprive us of the Keys of the Datary, we will try who ſhall be beſt able,
either he to take away the Keys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that are inviſible, or we to
preſerve thoſe of our Treaſure, which are palpable.</hi> From hence may
be gathered, that the Popes do<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104221:53"/>not aim ſo much at heavenly
as earthly things; wherefore they know very well, that they are in as much
danger of going to Hell as other men; and as a teſtimony that they fear it,
obſerve this, that they confeſs almoſt every day the ſins that they
commit. Now if they themſelves are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious of it, why may not the Romans
alſo doubt of the ſalvation of the Popes? To conclude this point, the
Popedom ſtill continues in the world, and they fall into the precipice that
have been bad Miniſters; and here to avoid all ſcruples, where we ſay
that ſuch a Pope is gone to Hell, we mean the Perſon, not the Dignity, the
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, not the Miniſtry; and if I my ſelf ſhould hear any one
ſay, that the Papacy is gone to Hell, I would give him the lye, if the Devil
himſelf were preſent; for he that will intermeddle and deliver ſuch
opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, muſt underſtand how to make diſtinctions in due form, and
ſeparate the Popedom from the Pope, leaving the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy in <hi>Rome,</hi> and
ſending the Pope from thence to Hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>This diſtinction of yours pleaſeth me; and it would do very
well to acquaint theſe Pious-ſtinkards therewith, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they loſe
both ſoul and body, if they<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104221:54"/>do but lend an eat to any
ſimple diſcourſe againſt the Popes perſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe perſons that ſeem ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, are all
Prieſts Sons and Friars Baſtards; it being their nature to be
ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, and ſuch you muſt imagine them to be; but men of ſtaid
judgment, both in publick and private, make themſelves very merry with
theſe Mock-Saints, and indeed who will be ſo fooliſh as to believe that
that Pope can be ſav'd, who tolerates, or ſhuts his eyes againſt, as we
may ſay, or to ſpeak more truly, commands Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Sodomy, Larceny, and
ſo many cheats as his Nephews put in practiſe, and with the Nephews the
whole Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But prethee let us return to our <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> and
leave theſe Nephews, in the Devils name, if you will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope and his Nephews are things link't together, that it is
impoſſible to treat of the one without the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I believe, that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs all theſe
diſorders it were neceſſary to deprive the Cardinals of the power of
electing the Pope, and make the Popedom Hereditary, as many other Dominions
are, which are far better govern'd; becauſe if it be left in the power, and
at the diſpoſal<pb n="101" facs="tcp:104221:54"/>of theſe Cardinals, the Nephews will
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies tyrannize over <hi>Rome</hi> and the Papacy; It being impoſſible
to find a Pope among the Cardinals without Nephews, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews without Boys:
If now the Whores have the liberty of Election, Whoredom would become
inſolent as Sodomy, becauſe they would make the whole <hi>Vatican</hi>
who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhly inclin'd; beſides that, the Ladies of greateſt quality would
pretend to have a ſhare with the Whores, to have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of coming to the
<hi>Vatican</hi> when they pleaſe; and it is moſt certain, that they will
never condeſcend to this, that they muſt kiſs the Popes Toe, and the
Whores receive the <hi>Oſculum Pacis,</hi> from the Popes own Lips. All
theſe diſtractions would be appeaſ'd, if we could once find out the way
to make the Popedom Hereditary; which might be done by the Popes taking a Wife;
and ſo neither the Ingles, nor Whores would have any pretence to the
<hi>Vatican;</hi> becauſe the Wife would lay Rats-bane in every corner, to
poiſon (as they uſe to do Mice) the Whores and Sodomitical Boys, that eat
up all the fat of the Church, and all the lard of the Court: But it were
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to find a Woman that would wear the Breeches, and not ſcruple
the giving her<pb n="102" facs="tcp:104221:55"/>Husband both boil'd and roſt meat;
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, both the pot and the pipkin would fly in pieces. If this cuſtom
be but once brought in among us, Oh, what brave doings would there be! O the
famous Nuptials that would be celebrated in ſuch a Marriage! Then after that
would be the greater rejoycing, when the moſt holy Popeſ's ſhould be
delivered, and of a Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling full of pontifical bleſſings, which ſhould
drop into the very arms of the Pope. What joy would there be at Court? What
rejoycing in the City? What feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the world over? But all theſe
joys would be nothing in compariſon of the ſolemn pomp that the moſt holy
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would make, to ſee young Popes of his bleſſed ſeed make the
Popedom for ever Hereditary to his Family. I am perſwaded, if the City of
<hi>Rome</hi> could once ſee a Pope with a Popeling in his arms, and careſs
him with ſo great affection, it would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her, and ſweeten her
afflictions. There would be neither little nor great, male nor female, but
would run to the <hi>Vatican</hi> to ſee the little Pope kiſs the reverend
beard of his Holineſs his Father. The Pope, as I conceit with my ſelf,
would be almoſt diſtracted with joy, and hug the young<pb n="103" facs="tcp:104221:55"/>Pope in his boſom, and I am of opinion he would be alwaies ſaying,
be thou hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, O my bleſſed ſweet heart, my graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous little Pope, my
dear Popeling; kiſs thy Father that made thee a Son, hug that Pope that begot
thee a young Pope; O my little Popeling, careſs him that gives thee a
Popedom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Peradventure the Pope cannot do ſo much as you talk of, and in
my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Cardinals would do well to make you Pope by the name of
<hi>Marforio</hi> the Firſt, and give you liberty to make choice of a
<hi>Marforia</hi> at your own diſcretion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you underſtand ſo
well how, to make much of Children. It is moſt certain, that it would waſh
away a great deal of that ſcandal that is in the world, and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man people
would receive no ſmall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by allowing the Pope a Wife; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all
the Prieſts and Friars would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his example, and marry likewiſe; and
by this means many of thoſe that wear the Bulls feather now, would be
without, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is the natural quality of thoſe that want, to ſeek to
be accommoadated by other mens goods. But yet however, this very act would have
its ſhare of impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the people would be alwaies, 
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:104221:56"/>more ſubject to grievances, if the Pope ſhould now
have a Wife; for, if at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Popes prove ſo covetous, and the
Clergy ſuch baſe Rogues, now they have no Children, how would they behave
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves if they had, when nature her ſelf would oblige them to enrich
the iſſue that ſprings from their own loyns?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Do you believe that the Popes and Clergy-men are without
Children? Figh, figh; thoſe that are Nephews by name, are Children by nature,
ſo that they could not act more wickedly than they have done already; but
there might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſome hope of a good end thereof; becauſe that when
miſchief is arriv'd to its height, it muſt neceſſarily have a fall; it
being very natural for thoſe things that are unſtable to deſcend when
they can ſoar no higher.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The example of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth ought to be alwaies
freſh in your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; he was one of thoſe Popes you mention'd; being a
married Prieſt, Biſhop, Cardinal and Pope; it being the common
diſcourſe now that he married <hi>Vanoccia Romana,</hi> which had been his
Concubine a long time, in a private Chamber, and in the preſence of a
Parochian Prieſt, his<pb n="105" facs="tcp:104221:56"/>great friend and Confeſſor.
That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuddainly gaining the papal Chair, he brought her into the
<hi>Vatican;</hi> keeping her not as a Concubine, but as a Wife; and the
Children that he had were not at all treated by him as Baſtards, but as
Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; he having alſo attempted to make the Popedom Hereditary to his
Family. There was no kind of ſacriledge which he did not commit, no tyranny
which he did not exerciſe, no barbariſm which he did not act, no Simony,
which he did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of, no Larceny which he was not guilty of. He
diſturb'd the publick peace of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> rob'd the Church of
her wealth, took away the ſacred veſſels from the Altar, ſold the
Eccleſiaſtical Dignities, let looſe the reins to all manner of vice, and
reduced <hi>Rome</hi> to the greateſt miſeries that were ever heard of, in
ſo many ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and deſtructions, which ſhe was brought unto by the
cruelty of her barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enemies: And what is the reaſon of all theſe
infamous actions and cruelties? Ask <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf, and he will
tell you that his Iſſues that ſtood before his eye did ſpur him on
thereunto; the ſight of his Children did deprive him of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and
transform'd him into a Devil.<pb n="106" facs="tcp:104221:57"/>Nor am I any waies offended
at this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the laſt place <hi>Alexander</hi> was not wiſer than
<hi>Solomon,</hi> and yet he to pleaſe his ſenſe, and ſatisfie his
Ladies, offred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to Idols <hi>l</hi> nor yet was he more inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
than <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of innocency, who did every way
tranſgreſs the divine commands, to obey his Wife. Now if a Pope, that had
no other than a Demy-wife, becauſe he eſpouſed her in private, did commit
ſo much wickedneſs, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd <hi>Chiſtendom</hi> to ſhed ſo
many tears, which are not a little reſented at this very day; what
devilliſh thing would not the others do if they had intire Wives? Let us be
content with this, that we have ſeen the lawful Children, or (if you
pleaſe) the Baſtards of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, without wiſhing
for worſe fortune. If we had not ſeen the difference there is between the
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, when in the hands of the Nephews, and in the fingers of the Children,
we might earneſtly deſire to have a married Pope; but undoubtedly the
Church could not ſtand long, becauſe the Popes would double their avarice,
in the ſame meaſure as the Parents affection to Children is doubled in
compariſon of that to the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews. The buſineſs concerning the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:104221:57"/>being thus judged at firſt ſight, who are every day
ſubject to fall out of the Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-pan into the Fire; it ſeems that it were
far better, and more to be deſir'd, to die once well, than a hundred times
ill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>By what I perceive, you would gain the better of it, and have
the victory; but you cannot reſolve with your ſelf to ask the She-Secretary
a copy of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. You would have the Pope marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and yet it is not
poſſible that you ſhould let him marry; and you would wiſh him without
a Wife, that you might give him a Wife according to your fancy. I for my part
agree with the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; let the Chriſtians chooſe them a Pope that
is a Batchelor, the Hereticks a married one, the Romans a Whore-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and
the Courtiers a Sodomite; and there let every one ſtand to his own, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
envying his compannions; and this ſeems to me the beſt remedy of all;
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the Pope be a Batchelor, he will be too violent againſt thoſe
that are married; if married, he will treat the Sodomitical Boys very
courſly, and if he be a Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, he will deſpiſe both thoſe that are
ſingle and married; but when every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath a Pope according to his own
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,<pb n="108" facs="tcp:104221:58"/>he cannot complain of any of them: The ſingle
Pope conforming himſelf to thoſe that are ſingle perſons; he that is
married with thoſe that are married, and ſo from hand to hand, every one
following the Pope that is of his own temper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>By what you ſay, it were requiſite, to impapate the whole
world, and fill the earth with Popes and Popelings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Let us return to our ſubject; for I ſee that the Devil
himſelf cannot make us leave off our diſcourſe of the Pope, when we once
enter upon it. Let us ſee a little what the Whores have done in their
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Even little or nothing, becauſe there are far more differences
among them, than among the Cardinals, who are ſo well skil'd in
diſſimulation and crafty dealings in their Conclaves; yet however 'tis
true, that the Pope ſhall be choſen without the aſſiſtance of the
Ladies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>How without the Ladies? what (a Devil) have the Ladies to do
with the Whores? I am aſtoniſhed to hear thy diſcourſe; and I even this
very morning was inform'd of I know not what in words, that happened in the
Whores conclave, between the Princeſs of <hi>Roſſana</hi> and
<hi>Brigidaccia</hi> a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-annuated<pb n="109" facs="tcp:104221:58"/>Whore, upon the
account of <hi>Odeſcalchi.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand that our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Dames do extreamly envy
the Whores condition, becauſe they are oblig'd to beg the advantage of
admiſſion from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Whores. Dear <hi>Marforio,</hi> if you had been
near this place, you had croſt your ſelf a hundred times; for in truth
there was ſuch a horrid bawling, that the fire of <hi>Mongibel</hi> could not
out noiſe. The Ladies did pretend that they had more reaſon to be at the
Election of the Pope among the Cardinals, than the Whores ever had; and on the
contrary the Whores did cry out, that the Election of the Pope did belong to
them, and not to the Ladies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But what were the Ladies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>They were infinite, the Whores did affirm the Election of the
Pope did belong to them, becauſe they had no ſmall party in the Colledge of
Cardinals; which the Ladies did oppoſe, ſaying, that they were altogether
Miſtreſſes of the affections of the Cardinals, who have left off their
purple Robes, rather than they would give one ſingle diſtaſt to a
ſingle Lady. To cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborate this aſſertion, the example of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal 
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:104221:59"/>
                  <hi>Camillo Panfilio</hi> was inſiſted upon, who did
not value the diſpleaſure of the Pope his Uncle, and <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi>
his Mother, to gratifie the Princeſs of <hi>Roſſano,</hi> upon whom he
had caſt his eye; deſpiſing the Cap, Lordſhip, Church and
<hi>Vatican,</hi> to marry this Lady whom he fancied. To this <hi>Signora Nina
Stagnarina,</hi> in the behalf of all the Whores in the Aſſembly, as a
perſon of good judgment, and able to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe how to preſerve the
reputation of the myſtery of Whoredom, anſwered, and ſaid, that even as
one Swallow did not make a Summer, ſo the example of <hi>Don Camillo</hi>
being but ſingle, was not ſufficient to ſtrengthen the Ladies
pretenſes; wherefore, if they would carry away the palm, it was neceſſary
that they produc'd more ſolid and pertinent reaſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But tell me a little, before you proceed any further, how do the
Ladies and the Whores agree among themſelves as to precedency? How did they
do to diſpoſe of places in the Aſſembly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ,</speaker>
               <p>In truth I know not all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars upon that ſubject;
but I am very certain that theſe three points were inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon:
Firſt, Whether this noble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhould be called the Aſſembly of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:104221:59"/>Whores, or of Ladies? Secondly, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Whores
ſhould have the ſame title as the Ladies? And thirdly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the
Preſidents ſhould be choſen by the Ladies or the Whores? As to the
firſt, there was no great debate about that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was agreed they
ſhould count both the one and the other, and ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in favour of
the greater number, that thereupon the Whores being found to be far more in
number than the Ladies, it was concluded that it ſhould be called the
Aſſembly of Whores, though the chiefeſt Ladies of the City were included
among them. They could not agree ſo eaſily about the ſecond, the Ladies
being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unwilling to give the Whores the title of Excellency; and on
the other hand the Whores were reſolv'd to make no kind of difference in that
place which was common both to the one and the other; but after long
oppoſition, the Whores yielded the title of Excellency to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
concluding that the Ladies ſhould be cal'd <hi>Moſt Excellent Whores,</hi>
and the others only by the name of <hi>Lady Whores.</hi> This ſecond point
being agreed upon, they came to diſcourſe the third; which was that of
electing the Preſidents, but the<pb n="112" facs="tcp:104221:60"/>diſputes were ſo
great, and the differences ſo irreconcileable, that it was judg'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
to draw lots for it, which fell to the Whores, to the great regret of the
Ladies, who could not without difficulty reſolve to be ſubject to a Whore
for their Preſidenteſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>It makes me in a extaſie, and ready
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o leap out of my skin. Then 'tis
the ſame thing as the world goes now, to ſay Whore, or Lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Don't wonder at that, Brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>Mundus ſemper
fuit Mundus, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nunquam mundus:</hi> The world hath ever been a world,
though it was never free from pollution, and cauſes have kept the ſame path
in nature, though we have ſteer'd another courſe, ſo that we could not
meet with that before, which we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter now. The Ladies and Whores have
almoſt ever been one and the ſame thing; and there never was any perſon
known, unleſs it were ſome poor Peaſant, that did not underſtand that
the title of Whore was included in that of My Lady; and if you never knew it
before, underſtand it now, that you may free your ſelf from the imputation
of an <hi>Ignaro;</hi> there being no other difference between them, but 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:104221:60"/>this, that the Lady is a private Whore, and the Whore a
publick one. The beſt bits are for the Ladies, who no ſooner ſpy out a
piece of well ſhap't fleſh, but they run upon it with more violence than a
Mule upon his Provender: What thing elſe can you imagine makes ſo many
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincials and Generals, ſo many Priors and Guardians, ſo many
Confeſſors and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, which frequent the Houſes of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ladies
in <hi>Rome,</hi> which cannot but bring ſcandal at leaſt both to Maid and
Men-ſervants? I would have you to know, that the Friars do not viſit the
Ladies to teach them to raiſe paſte, but to inſtruct them how to clap a
cap on their Husbands heads, not red, like the Cardinals, but of the Rook's
colour, which is much more common than the Cardinals Cap is; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every
one is allow'd as well Prieſt as Friar; Cardinal as Biſhop, Citizen as
Stranger, to beſtow the Cap of the Rooks colour: But the Cardinals Cap, no
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon gives but the Pope himſelf; which is the reaſon it is not ſo
common as the other. This, if I miſtake not, made the Ladies pretend to the
Election of the Pope; and they might rationally claim a right to the Popedom,
who are already all Popeſſes.<pb n="114" facs="tcp:104221:61"/>Let right take place; why
ſhould the Pope enjoy the Popedom, who makes few Cardinals, and not the
Ladies who create many? I do not underſtand how they can pretend to a
jurisdiction above the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, if they may not have the power of creating
Cardinals granted them, as well as the others; who in effect may be called
Popeſſes without a Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I believe theſe Lady Popeſſes and no Popeſſes did
reproach one another with many things in the Aſſembly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>They did caſt ſo many reproaches one upon the other, that if
<hi>Marino</hi> were alive, he would think it no hard task to furniſh
himſelf with invention to make a Poem of Whoredom like that of his
<hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> Among other things, whilſt they did argue about the making
a <hi>Preſidenteſs</hi> of the Aſſembly; <hi>Laura Ferareſſes</hi>
being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with, I know not what words ſpoken by a Lady, in diſparagement
of Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in general, ſtanding up, took up the Ladies words, with great
arrogancie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I expect, Ladies, that one of theſe dayes you ſhould
reſolve to baniſh us the City, to the end that you ſolely might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
the Company of Citizens and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; what ſtrange kind of malice is that 
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:104221:61"/>gnaws your mind? We have no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice for you, why have
you ſo much for us? We leave you almoſt all the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, whom you enjoy
at your pleaſure: You have your ſhare of Biſhops too, as well as we, and
poſſibly in a larger meaſure; for to us none reſort now but mean
people, who have no golden Chains, nor Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes of Diamonds to beſtow upon
you. The Roman Princes are yours, and the Princes Ambaſſadours alſo; what
then do you complain of? to what purpoſe is all this raſhneſs and
murmuring? This Aſſembly was brought together by us; and therefore the
<hi>Preſidenteſs</hi> ought to be of our chooſing: Moſt excellent
Ladies pray tell us, did we over come into your Aſſemblies, which are
almoſt without number, to make our pretenſes to any thing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Soft a little, what Aſſembly did that moſt Illuſtrious
little Whore mean? The Ladies manage their buſineſs private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and would
ſooner die with longing to eat raw fleſh, than truſt one another: And if
they do confide in any one, they do it with ſpecious pretenſes, and make
choiſe of ſuch perſons they have a power over. As for the reſt they
deſire to be reputed chaſt: What Aſſembly then are theſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:104221:62"/>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I do not underſtand <hi>Laura
Ferrareſſe's</hi> meaning; for to acquaint you with the buſineſs as
'tis, ſhe is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch depth that the Devil himſelf cannot
fathom her: However, ſhe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this her natural perfection, alwaies
endeavours to practiſe with perſons that are moſt fit to dive into: Yet I
conceit with my ſelf, that ſhe would hit them in the teeth with the
Feaſts, Balls &amp; Plays, and ſuch like Recreations, that uſe to be made
at <hi>Rome,</hi> where the whole company of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Gentlemen meet
together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I do not believe that there can be any injury done in thoſe
places, the cuſtoms of the Countrey being ſufficiently mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; this
might be alleaged indeed, if our Ladies were French, and not Italian; or they
were in <hi>France,</hi> where all liberty ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable is allow'd, and not in
<hi>Rome</hi> which is the Mother of virtue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>In ſum, I never met with ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Marforio</hi> in
the world as you are; you change your diſcourſe when you pleaſe; make
whom you will vertuous, marry in the morning and bury at night; and that which
is of greater moment, you can feign your ſelf ignorant, or wiſe, in time
and place when you pleaſe. It ſeems you think I have committed a hainous
crime,<pb n="117" facs="tcp:104221:62"/>in calling the Balls, Feaſts, and other
recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive meetings, which are made in <hi>Rome</hi> for the diverſion of
Ladies, Whoriſh meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but I perhaps do not abſolutely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all
that you your ſelf ſay to be true. Remove from you, I beſeech you, ſo
falſe a perſwaſion, and if you pleaſe change, your mind, by
diſabuſing your ſelf with thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices that perſwade you, that
the French are greater Libertines, than the Roman La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Know, that the
liberty which you ſay is uſed in <hi>France,</hi> is civility in
<hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; the civility of <hi>Italy</hi> is a licentiouſneſs in
<hi>France,</hi> where there are not found ſo many Popeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to creat
Cardinals as in <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, of ſuch as wear <hi>Acteons</hi>
Livery. The French Ladies are not ſo fooliſh as the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, for they
divert themſelves with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minades and conſtant viſiting one another at
their own Houſes; ſometimes they take occaſion to go to a newly wedded
Bride, ſometimes a Lady with Child, and ſometimes a ſick perſon, or
other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman; and thus they leave the Friars in their Cloyſters, the
Biſhops in their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Prieſts in their Cures: Whereas the Roman Dames whilſt the
French are walking for recreation, they are ſhut up in the Chamber of ſome
Houſe with a crafty preaching Friar, who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<pb n="118" facs="tcp:104221:63"/>her
the tranſubſtantiation of perſons, or transfiguration of occult cauſes.
Thoſe beaſts that are moſt cloſely kept up in the Don are the moſt
ſavage and cruel, and they never go forth but to ſeek after a prey. The
French Ladies are reclaim'd Beaſts, and the Italians Savage, and therefore
you had more need ſtand in fear of the Savage Italian, than the Tam'd French
Lady: when the Roman Lady goes out of the hole of her Chamber, you may be
ſure that ſhe looks after ſome prey, that ſhe may gnaw upon in her den;
and on the Contrary, the French that lives plentifully, hath no need to provide
for other food: If you had ever been in <hi>France,</hi> and obſerv'd with
what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſincerity, and civility of manners, the Ladies converſe
with Gentlemen, who make uſe of their liberty civilly, you would be of
opinion that our Ladies are Arch-whores to them. But in <hi>Rome,</hi> you may
eaſily perceive, that the Ladies go to Balls with no other deſign, but to
make ſome honeſt man out of his wits: Not to Plays, but to ſteal away the
heart of ſome poor Gentleman. What glances of the eyes? What geſtures? What
gentle bruſhes in paſſing by? What ſighs? What biting of the fingers?
What tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="119" facs="tcp:104221:63"/>on the Toe? What counterfeit ſmiles are
there ſeen at Plays, Feaſts, Balls, and Comedies, between Ladies and
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? And to what other end is this, but to manifeſt that all the
publick meetings of Ladies are but an Aſſembly of Whores? But this is
nothing, if they would be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with ſuch kind of meetings: but the
incivility of our Ladies reſts not here; they are not content to Court
wantonly at ſuch a Bride's Ball, or ſuch a Cardinals Comedy, but they give
themſelves up to profane the very Churches themſelves, to the great
ſcandal of faithful, pious and devout Chriſtians, and wicked and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Hereticks, where they make it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to fix their eyes wantonly
upon their Lovers, and oftentimes to contrive with their Hectors the way how
they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a nights lodging. And this I believe that <hi>la
Feraroſe</hi> did mean, and not without reaſon; becauſe it is certain
that there is far more miſchief done in one Aſſembly of Ladies, than a
hundred meetings of Whores, theſe being Whores in the Houſe, and Ladies in
the Church; whereas the Ladies (with reverence be it ſpoken to thoſe
private Actoreſſes) are Whores eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where. Truly the Ladies do deſerve 
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:104221:64"/>the title of moſt Excellent Whores, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have
the right of <hi>primogeniture,</hi> to that occupation, of the Whores
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Lady <hi>Nina della Canuccie,</hi> that now and then plays
the tame beaſt, and ſometimes the ſavage, defended this point with the
higheſt applauſe for the credit of the Whores, that could be, in preſence
of four Ladies and more of the chiefeſt of them; and that which is the
greateſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when flying out into paſſion, ſhe ſeems as if ſhe
would only tickle their ears, but ſhe toucht them to the quick. Yes, moſt
Excellent Ladies (ſaid ſhe) you do in all things deſerve the precedency
of us poor Whores who are born to gather up the crums that fall from your
Ladiſhips table? And reaſon good too, for we are but ſmall Whores,
whereas your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies are the greateſt Whores in the World!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But what did that great foul beaſt <hi>Nina</hi> intend by her
gathering up the drums that fell from the Ladies Table?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>I am not fully inform'd of that; the other night, having an
opportunity, which neceſſity forced me and of viſiting the Lady
<hi>Nina</hi> to ſpeak with a certain Gentleman, who co-habits with her
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies,<pb n="121" facs="tcp:104221:64"/>and ſerves to ſatisfie her corporal wants;
though ſome thinks he is a man that minds his ſouls health; I came in
juſt as they had entred upon the diſcourſe of the Ladies; wherefore I
intreated them not to wave it, and ſo they proceeded in their good arguments;
this moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentleman commending her extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that
ingenious conceit, which ſhe found out in the Aſſembly to overcome the
Ladies; meaning that concerning the Table, which you had a deſire to know;
and ſhe ſeeing her dear Gallant ready with an open mouth to receive hr
words, it did the more inflame her to ſpeak, giving him a thouſand
reaſons for that matter, and if by chance ſhe was defficient in any thing,
the Gentleman, who had reſided in the Houſes of more then four Ladies
beſides, did come in to her aſſiſtance, by rendring his own reaſons.
The whole ſubſtance of the diſcourſe conſiſted in this, that no men
followed the Whores, but ſuch as by chance had very ill fortune with the
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; or elſe ſuch who could not ſatisfie their hunger by taſting
all ſorts of food, by reaſon of the jealouſie of their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:104221:65"/>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>O, Now I underſtand your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and if it be ſo, the
Ladies deſerve the Seniority in Whoredom. But do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be
ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I do believe it, and he that doth not never ſaw woman. It
is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man to do that which is forbidden; whence it proceeds, that
the greater the privation is, the more is the will inflam'd to obtain the
deſire. And indeed we ſee how that daily Husbands murder their Wives, and
Wives run away from their Husbands. And what's the reaſon of this? Becauſe
all Laws and Honour are ſlighted, Ladies are daily ſtimulated on to ſeek
after thoſe men that are defended copulating with them; and the men thoſe
Ladies, that they ſhould let alone. In ſum, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, that the
Devil inſtigates us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to commit the moſt dangerous and great evils;
ſo that men being overcome by ſuch temptations, do beſiege the
For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs of the Ladies Chaſtity, aſſault the Virginity of young
Damſels, and play the madman more than the devil himſelf; nay worſe, to
violate the chaſtity of married Women and Widows, nay, of the very Nuns
themſelves, who are (to avoid thoſe incivilities) purpoſely ſhut up
under lock<pb n="123" facs="tcp:104221:65"/>and key, and live under the ſevere laws of a
Cloyſter: To go a whoring is natural, and therefore the Devil permits nature
to ſteer her own courſe, and he moves on to the acting of things
prohibited: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are bound to believe, that men now adaies go to
Whores, when they find they cannot attain to that, to which they are moſt
prompted; hence we may argue with reaſon, that the Whores have but little
advantage of the Ladies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I am apt to believe all you ſay, and am oblig'd to you for
your acquainting me with thoſe things that were before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to me. But if
you will pray fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me in ſome particulars as to thoſe
Cardinals that were in this ſo famous Aſſembly, in nomination for the
Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>The actions of moſt were ſurvey'd one after another: The
Ladies ſometimes propoſing one, and the Whores another. Their
propoſitions the Ladies did before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand ſtrive to deny with pregnant
reaſons; to the end they might bring it to paſs, that they ſhould
propoſe one according to their own fancy; but they had no ſooner
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd it, but the Whores oppoſ'd them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:104221:66"/>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould have propounded ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might have been
acceptable, that I might have heard their diſcourſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; but know
you not whether there was any thing mention'd the of Barbarini.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Above all; and to what purpoſe had this Aſſembly met,
without mentioning thoſe Cardinals who are in greateſt eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at
Court? They made long reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon their perſons; and produc'd ſo many
reaſons, that it is impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>But were the propoſitions made by the Ladies or Whores, or
elſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral by the one and the other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> was propoſ'd by all unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, and as
unanimouſly and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded by them, they judging it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
to admit him to the Papacy, who virifies the Sex, and goes for a Virgin. He
being excluded, the Ladies propoſ'd the Cardinal <hi>Antonio;</hi> in favour
of whom all the Whores alſo of the Aſſembly did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur; ſo that he was
look't upon by them all as a Pope: But this vogue did not laſt long; for the
Ladies being jealous becauſe the Whores did condeſcend to it with ſo much
affection, began to be ſuſpicious, that he did take the Whores part more 
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:104221:66"/>than theirs, that therefore he would ſum up together the
greateſt things he ever did in his life, and they ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of
that ſubject apart; and obſerve near hand the Curtezans proceedings, who
ſtill cryed out, that this Lord ſhould be made Pope, who for ſo many
years had carried himſelf ſo affectionatly to the Sex. The Ladies thought
fit to enumerate, as near as was poſſible, all the Ladies, with whom the
Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> had been pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately concern'd; and if the number of
the Ladies ſhould exceed, that then he ſhould be admitted to the Papacy,
otherwiſe, he ſhould be excluded. But a juſt account being made, it was
found, that he had—twice as many Whores as Ladies; ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more
ado, they declar'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt it. The Curtezans on the other hand,
underſtanding that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, were very forward with them in the
defenſive part; ſaying, that they did deceive themſelves; for the account
that they had given in had no ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the number of Ladies, as well
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons, and Virgins as Widows, with whom the Cardinal
<hi>Antonio</hi> had kept com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was innumeralbe, having had a deſign to
the buſineſs, but not ſecreſie; ſo that<pb n="126" facs="tcp:104221:67"/>he was
never very careful of that in his exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe with Whores, eſteeming all this
to be to his honour, and an effect of Nobility. Now the Ladies were almoſt
reſolv'd to condeſcend to his Election, when the Dutcheſs of —
roſe up and ſaid; let us for all this think of ſome other Lady
Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociats, becauſe this were to cut our own throats. Let us have a care
of making one Pope, who hath been more zealous to defend a filthy deformed
Slut, than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thoſe Ladies that were the greateſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites. Let
us remember what he did heretofore to my Lord <hi>Palotta,</hi> for cauſing
that infamous Strumpet <hi>Cecca Buffona</hi> to be whipt, who acted the
domineering Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, becauſe ſhe lay with the Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi>
who then raigned. If we ſhould make him Pope, all the Whores would be
She-Cardinalst, and we muſt go and beg protection from our enemies. This
diſcourſe did ſtir up the mind of the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans the more to maintain the
argument; and there had happened a mutiny, if the Preſidentes had not
moderated the violence of the Whores; ſaying, it may be we ſhall all be
miſtaken, therefore I judge it more fit to think of another ſubject. This
Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal is now old, and old age in men brings<pb n="127" facs="tcp:104221:67"/>them to
repent of the ſins of their youth; that therefore I am apt no believe, that
we can expect no other, than the affront of be-being baniſhed his preſence;
it being the quality of old men to deſpiſe that which they have had the
fruition of, and can no longer enjoy. And if withal he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any
remains of good will towards us, he would have no food, but ſuch as is fit to
create him an appetite; ſo that one way or other, we ſhould loſe our
time; and ſo much the more in regard that he had made many Ladies and Whores
Cardinaleſſes, he would be gravel'd to create a Popeſs among, and may be
he would make one that would be jealous of all. The Ladies of pleaſure being
ſatisfied with this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they, together with the Ladies, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded
Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> and declar'd him incapable of pretending to the
Popedom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>And did they not mention Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Charles Barbarino</hi>
their Nephew, who is young, and in hopes of being Heir to his Uncles?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>There was ſome what ſaid of him, but the Ladies would not
endure to hear it, by reaſon of the diſparagement he had done the female
Sex, deſpiſing the Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture, by not marrying, the Ladies 
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:104221:68"/>arguing from hence, that if he had denied a Princeſs,
who was offered him in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, he would not be ſollicitous to ſeek one.
The Whores ſaid neither good nor bad of him, becauſe they never had the
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his converſation, but thereupon they agreed with the Ladies that
had exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him. The example of <hi>Cecca Buffana,</hi> who was cauſ'd to
be whipt by <hi>Palotta,</hi> mentioned to the company of Ladies, made ſome
impreſſion upon their ſpirits, and did penetrate the thoughts of all
their Excellencies, who endeavoured, the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barina</hi> being excluded, to
promote Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Palotta,</hi> as one that abhorr'd the name of a Whore,
having alwaies ſhewed a himſelf perſecutor of Whoredom, and never fail'd
to protect the Ladies in and by all means whatſoever. Some of them ſaid
they muſt have time to conſider of it well; for theſe were things that
could not be done a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time: And among the reſt one Lady of the
Houſe of <hi>Conti</hi> argued thus: If we were aſſured that Cardinal
<hi>Palotta</hi> would deal with all the Curtezans of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he did
with <hi>la Cecca,</hi> we had good reaſon to endeavour his promotion; but
who can aſſure us that he is really the ſame perſon, as he ſeems to
be? Who knows, whether<pb n="129" facs="tcp:104221:68"/>the whipping of <hi>la Cecca</hi>
was done out of an earneſt affection, or vain-glory: I am apt to think out of
vain-glory, to let the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty underſtand that he loved juſtice, without
reſpect of perſons; and by this way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to gain the love of the
people; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, many are of opinion, that <hi>la Cec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> had never
been whip't, if ſhe had not been Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi>'s She-friend; in
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of whom, 'tis thought <hi>Palotta</hi> prov'd ſo rigorous. It is
the property of ſuch kind of men, to declare themſelves enemies to what
they love: For my part I will not ſwear for his honeſty, and I underſtand
what I ſay; he is a man as well as other men are; and loves to keep company
with raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally people, therefore he entertains him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the morning with
them, and at night with Friars, who in <hi>Rome</hi> are Hectors to certain of
the vileſt Whores; ſo that there is little hope there ſhould be any great
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters done for us. For all this the Ladies did ſtill favour
<hi>Palotta;</hi> the whipping of <hi>la Cec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> being imprinted in their
minds; though this was thrown in his diſh by the Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans, that this
<hi>Palotta</hi> having cauſ'd the Prelats Whores to be whipt, he ſhould
not have omitted the whipping the Popes La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alſo. It ſufficeth to
ſay, that the<pb n="130" facs="tcp:104221:69"/>Whores did manage their buſineſs ſo
well, that they excluded him, forcing him to take a more dangerous leap than
that he took in <hi>Portugal</hi> to ſave his life by jumping out of a
window.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>So it ſeems this Cardinal is neither of God, nor the Devil,
and can neither ſatisfie the Whores, nor the Ladies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps, if he were made Pope, he would be of another mind, and
would out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly manifeſt what is found inwardly. His excluſion was the
cauſe that they fell upon <hi>Tapetto Ginetti;</hi> but they no ſooner
began to mention him, but he was exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a general conſent; the
Ladies, by reaſon of his mean and baſe extract; and the Curtezans,
becauſe of his Covetouſneſs. <hi>Laura Maſſa</hi> however did not
fail to give her aſſiſtance, not becauſe ſhe was inclin'd to favour
thoſe that were covetous; for ſhe lov'd prodigality in the exceſs far
more, then moderated covetouſneſs, but to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Siſter-hood,
that had ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar intereſt in ſome of <hi>Ginetti's</hi> Nephews;
the reſt did altogether jear, at <hi>Laura Maſſa</hi> for her
recommending him, hiſſing at her behind her back with very much ſcorn.
<hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netti</hi> being quite out of hope of gaining the Chair, they began to
muſter up their forces<pb n="131" facs="tcp:104221:69"/>for the Cardinals
<hi>Grimaldi</hi> and <hi>Urſini,</hi> the Ladies extreamly deſiring their
promotion; the others did not diſlike them; but ſaid, it would be no good
policy to beſtow the Popedom upon frenchified Italians, who might frenchifie
all <hi>Italy;</hi> ſo that they chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their minds; though very much
againſt their inclination, to advance the benefit of their publick
intereſt; for indeed there was not one Lady in the Aſſembly, but
deſir'd either the one or the other of theſe two perſons for many
reſpects; and particularly, for the hope they had to ſee the French liberty
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd in <hi>Rome;</hi> being that theſe Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals enjoy it, and make
a very fine uſe of it. They came then to viſit the Spaniſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
naming them one by one; the Whores now reckoning up the virtues of the one, and
the Ladies of the other. The Ladies were content the Whores ſhould make
choice of one to pleaſe themſelves, provided he were a Spaniard; and the
Whores made the Ladies the ſame proffer, the Arragoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans only excepted, as a
people that did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much affect <hi>Rome;</hi> yet neither the one nor the
other could by any means find out a good Subject among ſo many Spaniolizers,
to ſuit with the humour of the Aſſembly; but excluded them all for their
damnable<pb n="132" facs="tcp:104221:70"/>pride, by which they made themſelves odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to
all the female Sex, who love to ſee men humble, as well riding as on foot;
ſo they endeavoured to bring the other Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans upon the Stage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Among theſe She Conclaviſts, were there not divers factions,
as there uſ'd to be in the Conclave of Cardinals?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>Not among the Ladies, but among the Whores there were, yet there
was no great notice taken of it; becauſe the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faction was thrice as
well furniſh't as all the reſt in number; however the Spaniſh Faction was
grown ſomewhat numerous by the arrival of many ſordid baggages newly come
from <hi>Spain,</hi> with the Catholick Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour: But as for the French
Faction, it was very weak they having but a few little Whores, who liv'd upon
ſome lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings that did advance the old Italian Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezans. The Princeſs
<hi>Colomia</hi> did pretend at firſt, that ſhe was capable of bringing in
a party of Ladies, either French Ladies, Italianiz'd, or Italians frenchified;
but the French Ladies Italianiz'd, would not agree with the Italian Ladies
frenchified; and therefore the Princeſs, who did not know in her conſcience
whether ſhe was Italian or French, being doubtful whether ſhe 
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:104221:70"/>was born in <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Italy;</hi> did not
much care to ſhew her ſelf obſtinate in making a Faction, but followed
the reſt, and aſſiſted them them in their Councils with her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
gentile humour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>This Princeſs has a good wit, and a ſweet flowing tongue,
and deſerves to be half French and half Italian.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſ.</speaker>
               <p>But to come to our buſineſs; the female Conclaviſts being
thus in a confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and in ſuſpence, not being able to find out a Pope
to their ſatisfaction, having now ſifted the point concerning the Cardinals
more exactly, did think to effect their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs by promoting the Cardinal
<hi>Brancac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio;</hi> for whom the two <hi>Velletrane</hi> ſpake, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
the Aſſembly with the quality of the perſon; ſaying, that this Lord
being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to pleaſure, and to the ſatisfying of his own appetite;
ever allowed of, and granted licences for Balls and Comedies, and continual
Masks; which are the moſt convenient things to bring ſtore of men to his
Apartment; he would not fail to make a continual Carneval, and make Lent
ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which makes us for the moſt part eat up what we gain'd during the
ſmall time that the Carneval laſts. But theſe are not all his good
qualifications; there being<pb n="134" facs="tcp:104221:71"/>other conſiderations, that
ſhould plead for his Election. If we ſhould make this man Pope, it will
prove for the good of us all, becauſe he having an infinite number of
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, the Houſe of <hi>Brancaccio</hi> (which you know very well)
having ſuch nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous branches, he will bring little leſs than half the
Kingdom to <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that you gain advantage by them all. The Ladies
ſmil'd at this propoſition, and anſwered in ſhort, that that vulgar
Italian Proverb, which the Romans know by common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to be true, was
ſufficient to exclude <hi>Brancaccio,</hi> viz. The Neopolitans are large
mouth'd, but cloſe fiſted. 'Tis very true indeed (the Whores ſaid) we had
need of another kind of men then the Neapolitans are; it were more
neceſſary for us to ſeek out a Poliſh or German Pope, that would bring
hither along with him a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe Mamalucks, that are
open-handed and narrow mouth'd. <hi>Adrianella;</hi> who had no other deſign
then the promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi> her Confident, perceiving that
the propoſing of a Pope who had many Relations was not il-reſented by the
Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, began thus to expreſs her ſelf: Moſt noble femal
Companions, if the reaſons for a Pope with a numerous Family may 
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:104221:71"/>take place in this Conclave; certainly we ought not to
quit Cardinal <hi>Roſpiglioſi,</hi> who hath three parts of four of the
Citizens of the City of <hi>Piſtoia,</hi> the place of his Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his
Relations, who will all of them forſake their dwellings to come and live in
<hi>Rome,</hi> and thus there will be no jealouſie among us; becauſe every
Lady, and every Whore will have one of this Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews for her friend.
Beſides, he being a great lover of the Muſes, he will grant us liberty to
to make publick meetings ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our pleaſure, and ſuffer thoſe
Geldings and Superiors that are of our opinion to come among us. Weigh this
well in your minds, my moſt dear She-Companions, becauſe theſe
propoſitions are not to be buried in oblivion. <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s propoſal
was well reliſh't by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, the major part of the She-Concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſts
being in a manner ſatisfied, ſo that they were about to make an immediat
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion in favour of <hi>Roſpiglioſi,</hi> but were forc't to leave
off by reaſon of a great noiſe that began to be raiſ'd without doors, by
thoſe Abbats, Prelats, and other of their Gallants, every one whereof ſtaid
in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of his Miſtris to wait upon her home. The occaſion of the
noiſe was,<pb n="136" facs="tcp:104221:72"/>that having had a relation of the words of
<hi>Adrianella;</hi> and underſtanding that now the Female-Conclaviſt,
would create <hi>Roſpig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioſi</hi> Pope, who had ſo many Nephews and
Grand-children, the Gallants grew jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous upon this, fearing they ſhould
loſe what they had; ſince it is the property of the Popes Nephews to
diſpoſſeſs thoſe that are in poſſeſſion, to put themſelves
in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for this reaſon they cried out that
<hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi> might not be made Pope, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burthened with ſo
many friends. This rumor was ſo loud, that there was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to
adjourn the Aſſembly, and refer all things to another day. This is all I
can acquaint you with at preſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>I return you thanks, and will find out ſome other time to
underſtnad the reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
